<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A treatise of prayer, and of the fruits and manner of prayer. By the most Reuerend Father in God Iohn Fisher Bishop of Rochestre, Preist and most eminent Cardinall of the most holy Catholike Church, of the title of S. Vitalis. Translated into English by R.A.B.</title>
            <title>Tractatus de orando Deum. English</title>
            <author>Fisher, John, Saint, 1469-1535.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1640</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 123 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 95 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A00765</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 10890</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S115046</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99850265</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99850265</idno>
            <idno type="VID">15454</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A00765)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 15454)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 797:09)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A treatise of prayer, and of the fruits and manner of prayer. By the most Reuerend Father in God Iohn Fisher Bishop of Rochestre, Preist and most eminent Cardinall of the most holy Catholike Church, of the title of S. Vitalis. Translated into English by R.A.B.</title>
                  <title>Tractatus de orando Deum. English</title>
                  <author>Fisher, John, Saint, 1469-1535.</author>
                  <author>Roe, Alban, 1583-1642, attributed name.</author>
                  <author>Anderton, Robert, attributed name.</author>
                  <author>Batt, Antonie.</author>
                  <author>R. A.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[16], 271, [1]   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By Will: Baudry,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Printed att Paris :</pubPlace>
                  <date>M. DC. XXXX [1640]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Another edition of Fisher, John.  A godlie treatisse declaryng the benefites, fruites, and great commodities of prayer.</note>
                  <note>Translator R.A.B. = R.A. B[enedictine].--STC.</note>
                  <note>Includes (following page 243): The armour of S. Ephræm.</note>
                  <note>Translation has been attributed to Robert Anderton, Alban Roe, and (because of a misreading of the initial indicating the translator's religious affiliation) Antonie Batt.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect; much print show-through.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Prayer --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:15454:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:15454:1"/>
            <p>A TREATISE OF PRAYER, AND OF THE FRVITS AND MANNER OF PRAYER.</p>
            <p>By the moſt Reuerend Father in God IOHN FISHER Bishop of Rocheſtre, Preiſt and moſt eminent Cardinall of the moſt holy Catholike Church, of the title of S. Vitalis.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Tranſlated into English by R. A. B.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Printed att Paris by Will: Baudry</p>
            <p>M.DC.XXXX.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="modern_bookplate">
            <pb facs="tcp:15454:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>bookplate</figDesc>
                  <head>Academiae Cantabrigiensis Liber.</head>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:15454:2"/>
            <head>TO THE VERY HONORABLE AND VERTVOVS LADYE THE LADYE ELIZABETH HERBERT, Wife to the honorable Sin Percy Herbert, of Powis Caſtle in Montgomerie ſhire.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>ADAME,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>The noble favours I have received
<pb facs="tcp:15454:3"/>from your Ladishipp have not onely made me ſtudious to preſerve a gratefull mind in my ſelfe, But alſo encoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged me to vndertake theſe ſmal paines in your Ladyshipps behalfe. I know good MADA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ME, that by your day<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly exerciſe in prayer, you have atteined to a great perfection in that art: Yet with all, I know your Ladiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hipps humilitie to be ſuch, as you will not ſcorne nor diſdeigne
<pb facs="tcp:15454:3"/>to better your know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge from the inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions of the moſt able, and moſt pious vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding of the age in which he lived. MADAME, I pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent heere vnto your Ladyſhipp a Treatiſe of the moſt Reuerend Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Iohn Fisher Bishop of Rocheſter, Preiſt &amp; moſt eminent Cardinall of the holy Roman Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholike Church; as you ſee, MADAME, ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiently recommended hy thoſe titles he deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vedly
<pb facs="tcp:15454:4"/>obteined, corre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpondent to the ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues of his moſt holy and bleſſed life. My care hath onely been to render him faythfullie and for your Ladishipps benefitt, as the gravitie of the argument requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res, not giuing him any other orname<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t the that of truth, which I ſuppoſie makes it more agrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to your Ladyshipps vertues, and with all I deſire, it may be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted from him, who glories in nothing mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re
<pb facs="tcp:15454:4"/>then the title of bein<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>MADAME,</salute> 
               <signed>Your Ladyshipps moſt humble ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant and beadſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man. R. A. B.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="approbation">
            <pb facs="tcp:15454:5"/>
            <head>APPROBATIO.</head>
            <p>NOs Frater Clemens Rayne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus Congregationis Anglica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nae Ordinis Sancti Benedicti, Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byter &amp; Monachus eiuſdemque Congregationis Praeſes Generalis: per praeſentes facultatem concedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus typis mandandi deuotum Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctatum Reuerendiſſimi in Chriſto Patris Iohannis Fisheri Epiſcopi Roffenſis, &amp; Romanae Eccleſiae Cardinalis Eminentiſſimi, de Ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tione à Reuerendo Patre R. A. eiuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demquc Ordinis &amp; Congregationis noſtrae in idioma Anglicum tradu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctum. In cuius rei ſidem his ſubſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pſimus, ſigillumque noſtrum appo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuimus die ſexto Februarij, anno Domini 1640.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Fr. CL. RAYNERVS Praeſes Generalis. Locus † ſigilli.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="index">
            <pb facs="tcp:15454:5"/>
            <head>AN INDEX OF THE CHAPTERS.</head>
            <list>
               <head>THE FIRST PART.</head>
               <item>HOw We may alwa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>Chapt. I. pag. 1.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The firſt reaſon why God is to be prayed vnto. <hi>Cha. II. p. 17.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The ſecond reaſon why God is to be prayed vnto. <hi>Cha. III. p. 27</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The third reaſon why God is to be prayed vnto. <hi>Cha. IV. p. 37.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The laſt reaſon why God is to be prayed vnto. <hi>Cha. V. p. 44.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>THE SECOND PART.</head>
               <item>Of the three cheife fruits of prayer. <hi>Chap. I. p. 53.</hi>
               </item>
               <pb facs="tcp:15454:6"/>
               <item>Of the firſt fruite of prayer, to wit of meritt. <hi>Cha. II. p. 58.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Of the ſecond fruite of prayer which is to obteining of the thing we pray for. <hi>Chap. III. p. 63.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Of the third fruite of prayer which is ſpirituall ſweetneſſe. <hi>Chap. IV. p. 70.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>THE TRIRD PART.</head>
               <item>Of the manner of prayer. <hi>Chap. I. p. 85.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Vn to what thing we ought chei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fely to attend when we pray. <hi>Chap. II. p. 87.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>How long our prayer ought to be. <hi>Chap. III. p. 201.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Whether prayer of the heart one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be more profitable then that wich is made both with heart and ſpeech. <hi>Cha. IV. p. 217.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <div type="prayer_preparation">
            <pb facs="tcp:15454:6"/>
            <head>OF PREMEDITA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, before Prayer.</head>
            <p>VVhen you intend to of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer the Sacrifice of pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yer, &amp; prayſes, to almighty God, and prepare you to prayer.</p>
            <p>Firſt, recall your Sences, and gather together your wit res, &amp; with an humble, at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentiue, and deuout minde, lift vp your heart to almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty God: Reuerontly ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding vpright, with your hands ioyned before your breſt, and lifted vp.</p>
            <p>Pauſe then à little while, and aduiſedly confider with
<pb facs="tcp:15454:7"/>your ſelfe wherefore you come, whereabout you goe, &amp; what buſines you now take in hand.</p>
            <p>Alſo, before whom you are preſent, the petitions you wil aske, and the offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring you meane to make.</p>
            <p>Remembre you are nowe, before a moſt mighty &amp; di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine Maieſtie; The Creator and Redeemer of yourſelfe, and all Mankinde, whom in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite number of Angels, and al the Celeſtial multitude do continually adore and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship, with feare and trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling.</p>
            <p>And your ſelfe, a moſt wretched &amp; vnworthie crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, fraile, vnſtable, fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling from him: dull, and
<pb facs="tcp:15454:7"/>vnapt to cal vpon him. And yet his mercie is ſo much, and his goodneſſe ſo great, that he is euer, readie to heare, and gratiouſlie to graunt, your lawfull reque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes, and to receaue you when you come vnto him: and alſo to forgiue you all your offences, when you are heartelie ſorie and aske mercie for them.</p>
            <p>Likewiſe, he is one that hath, and doth moſt boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tefully beſtowe vpon you, all things neceſſarie for bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die and ſoule: and hath and doth defende and keepe, fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ede and nourish you, and all creatures.</p>
            <p>Then thinke, that it is before this diuine Preſence,
<pb facs="tcp:15454:8"/>before the which you pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume to enter, and to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent your ſelfe: to intreate, beſeech, and require mercy, and forgiueneſſe of ſinnes, for your ſelfe and all others: and to offer the ſacrifice of Prayſe, and Thankeſgiuing vnto him.</p>
            <p>Therefore with all humili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie and reuerence proſtrate your ſelfe at the feete of his mercie: and indeuour with deuotion, to accompliſh that you come for. But before you begin your prayers, that you may the rather offer them with cleanes of heart, and giue thanks to God, not onely for his benefites, but chiefly for his goodneſſe in himſelfe, make it fully
<pb facs="tcp:15454:8"/>knowen to your heart, as true, that it is vncertaine whether you shall liue to the end of your Prayers or not: Indeuour therefore that they may be ſuch, as if it should ſo happen before you had ended the, that ſo, through the mercie of God, they may be acceptable vnto him, for the full forgiuenes of your offences, and the receauing you into his grace and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour.</p>
            <p>And that you may the more perfectly beginne, continue, and end, all your prayers, and other good ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, in the Name, and to the honour, and glorie of GOD, the moſt holie and bleſſed Trinitie: and haue
<pb facs="tcp:15454:9"/>in minde his great goodneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe towardes you, and giue thankes for them: and alſo that the Paſſion of our Lord, may take the more effect, the benefite of it may be imparted, the fruite there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of inioyed: and in all ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall practiſes, remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred; You may, if it pleaſe you, begin your Prayers, in maner as followeth. Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ekely falling on your knees, your heart and ioyned han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des being eleuated to God.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:15454:9"/>
            <head>A TREATISE OF PRAYER, AND OF THE FRVITS AND maner of praying.</head>
            <div n="1" type="part">
               <head>THE FIRST PART.</head>
               <div n="1" type="chapter">
                  <head>Hw we may alwaiſe pray. <hi>CHAPT. I.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>OR as much as that which Chriſt our Saviour affirmeth in the ghoſpell of Saint Luke to witt <hi>thac, We ought alwayſe
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:15454:10"/>to pray,</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cerneth all Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, who ſeeth not how much it doth avayle euery Chriſtian to apply himſelfe moſt diligently to prayer, and in no wiſe to neglect ſo neceſſarie and profitable a thing, for any vaine and hurtful pleſures? wherefore that wee may feele the more ſweetneſſe in prayer. <hi>Firſt,</hi> it will be proffitable to haue at hand ſome motieues, by which as with certaine ſpurrs (ſo oft as we grow could) we may ſtirre vp our ſelues to prayer.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Secondly,</hi> it wil not meane<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly helpe vs, if we conſider the excelle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t fruits and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moditie that many haue ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teined by prayer, for by
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:15454:10"/>that mea<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s alſo wes hall eaſily ſtirre vp our ſelues to that exerciſe. And <hi>laſtly</hi> it will proffitt much to know the manner which euery one ought chelfely to obſerue in praying: ſeing that in euery worke the maner of doeing beinge knowne, is of no ſmall moment to perfect the work it ſelfe that we goe about.</p>
                  <p>Of theſe three things the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>refore in order we purpoſe by Gods aſſiſtance to ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke,<note place="margin">Thres prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall points <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>and<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lied in this tre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>atiſe.</note> to wit. of the neceſſitie, of the fruits, and of the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of praying. But becauſe the foreſaid words of our Saviour moue ſome ſcruple in many, it will not be amiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe if we firſt declare in what
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:15454:11"/>manner they may be vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood.</p>
                  <p>Firſt aſſuredly it is moſt true,<note place="margin">u. 18.</note> which Chriſt our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour ſaid we <hi>ought alwayſe to pray.</hi> For there is no mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of time in which prayer is not neceſſary for vs. Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerthe leſſe God almightie is not ſo ſeuere an exactor, as to oblidge vs to continual prayer of the lipps, which certeinly no man euer did or could obſerve. But becau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe there neuer paſſeth any moment of time wherein we doe not exceedinglie ſtand in neede of his divine aſſiſtance, Therefore our great neceſſitie enforceth vs, by continuall prayer alwaiſe to implore his ai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de.
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:15454:11"/>For who Knoweth not (if he diligently conſider) that if God ſhould With<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>draw his helping hand from vs, we ſhould inſtantlie then returne into duſt and aſhes? neyther is there any man, who of hymſelfe can continue the leaſt mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of time, for as holy Iob ſayth, <hi>In his hand is the ſoule of euery living thing.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Iob</hi> A ſims<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>litude.</note> For ſoe it is with euery one of vs, as if one ſhould hang by a rope in a coffine ouer a deepepitt, for he doubtleſſe ſtands in great neede of his helpe who holdeth the rope in his hand and keepeth the other from faling in to the pitt. For ſo ſoone as he withdra weth his hand from the rope, he that
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:15454:12"/>before was held vp, doth in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly fall healdlo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g in to the pitt. Neyther would it be otherwiſe with euery one of vs, if God ſhould not inceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſantly ſuſteine vs With his ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d. He holdeth the cord in his ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, leaſt wee inſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly be brought to nothing, to omitt many other eminent dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, which euery moment hang ouer our heads. Who therefore is ſo groſſe and blind, as not to conſider, that there is no time, yea no mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of time, wherein it is not neceſſarie for vs, to call on God, and to implore his gratious helpe, and aſſiſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce. And this is the meaning of thoſe words, that <hi>we ought alwayſe to pray.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="7" facs="tcp:15454:12"/>
                  <p>But becauſe according to this ſenſe there is no man that doth fulfill this ſaying of our Saviour by actuall prayer, as they call it, that is, who doth alwayſe euery moment pray, therefore an other ſenſe is to be found. out. Wherefore this ſaying of Chriſt may be vnderſtood an other way, to wit, that which wee ſhall now decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re.</p>
                  <p>One of the ancient Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes being dema<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded in what maner he did ſatisfie that ſaying of Chriſt,<note place="margin">The firſt vvay hovv vve may a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lvvayſe pray The <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> Euths<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis in the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                           <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                        </gap> holy fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phabeto <hi>26.</hi> part. <hi>12</hi> litera <hi>4.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>we ought a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lwayſe to pray,</hi> anſwered for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thwith That after he had en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded his dayly prayers, the reſt of the time, according to the abilitie of his body,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:15454:13"/>he ſpent in manuall labours, by which meanes it came to paſſe that he dayly gaigned ſomethinge, whereby he notonly ſuſteined himſelfe, but alſo in ſome ſort other poore people, and thoſe he ſayd did pray for him, ſo of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten as the care he was bound to take of his bodie, would not permitt him to doe it himfelſe, whoſe opinion is agreable to holy Scripture which Sayth,<note place="margin">Eccl. 19.</note> 
                     <hi>Hide thy almes in the boſome of the poore, and it ſhal pray for thee</hi> Loe heere how the Scripture confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth that our almes pray for vs. If therefore any one ſhal diligently imploy himfelſe in the workes of mercy, if he defend the fatherleſſe
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:15454:13"/>and orphans, if he comfort poore widdows being deſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute of all conſolation, if he protect from iniuries thoſe that are violently oppreſſed. And laſtly if he adminiſter helpe to thoſe are in want, ſoe that in the meane time he neglecteth not, the times of prayer inſtituted by the Church, he alſo ſhall fulfill the ſayd words of Chriſt, for he alwayſe eyther pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth himſelfe, or hath his al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes praying for him, which will ſupplie what is wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of his owne prayers (we<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ought alwaiſe to pray.)</p>
                  <p>In this ſenſe alſo may the aforeſayd ſaying of Chriſt <hi>we ought alwayſe to pray,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">The ſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dvv<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>y hovv vvem<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>y a vvay <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </note> be vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood that is we ought al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waiſe
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:15454:14"/>to liue well and dowell, which, we may doe, cue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>when we ſleepe. For whenſoeuer we ſleepe or wake, when wee walke, or ſitt, when we eate or drinke, when we are mole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted or conforted; laſtly w<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hatſoeuer we doe or ſuffer, if they be referred truely to the glorie and honour of God, doubtleſſe they belong to a good and vpright life. Othe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rwiſe Saint Paul would not haue commanded the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinthians that whatſoeuer they did theyſhoud doe it to the glorie of God,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 10.</note> ſaying, <hi>whether yee eate or drinke or what elſe yee doe, doe it te the glory of God.</hi> And truely if God be moued by our words, to be bene fieiall vnto
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:15454:14"/>vs, queſtionleſſe he is much more moued thereto by our good workes, ſeing that wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes doe ſupplie the place of words. And therefore the diuine benignitie is moued with our workes, which we doe with a deſire to pleaſe his diuine Majeſtie, ſeing they doe expreſſe the force of our prayers, yea, and much more forcibly, then doe the words themſelues. Whoſoeuer therefore doth referre to the glorie of God all that he doth and ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth; prayeth euery moment and alwayſe ſatisfieth the affore ſayd ſaying of Chriſt. For he that alwayſe dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cteth all his actions to the glorie of God may be ſayd
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:15454:15"/>not vnworthely alwayſe to pray. But although theſe words, <hi>we ought alwayſe to pray,</hi> may be vnderſtood ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to this ſenſe, yett bycauſe Chriſt maketh a difference betwixt prayer and workes, and maketh al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes, prayer, and faſting as diſtinct things, therefore we wil now ſett downe the third way how this ſaying may be vnderſtood.</p>
                  <p>Saint Paul therefore ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniſheth the Theſſalonia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s that they ſhould inceſſantly pray.<note place="margin">
                        <hi>The third vvay hovv vve may alvvay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe pray</hi> 1. Theſ ſal. 2. Ro. 1.1. Theſ ſal. 1.</note> 
                     <hi>Pray yee</hi> (ſayth he) <hi>wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thout intermiſsion.</hi> Ānd in ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me other places of his epiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tles he affirmeth that <hi>he was mindfull</hi> (of ſome) <hi>in his prayers without intermiſsion.</hi> Beſides in
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:15454:15"/>the acts of the Apoſtles it is ſayd that whilſt S. Peeter was kept in priſon <hi>Prayer was made by the Church without in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termiſsion to God for him.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Act. 12</note> By which words it doth clearely appeare that a true Chriſtian in euery worke, euen when he ſleepeth, doth alwayſe pray: which cannot betrue, vnleſſe by prayer, we vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand the continuall deſire of the mind,<note place="margin">Prayer a conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire of the mind A ſimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litude.</note> which is alwayſe flourishing, and mouing in the heart: For euen as one in priſon bound with iron fet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of great weight moued with the irkſomneſſe of the miſeries and affliction which he ſuffereth, doth veheme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly deſire and ſeeke his libertie; and, if he ſhal conceiue any
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:15454:16"/>hope of his deliuery he in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſantly wisheth and deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth to be freed from that impriſonment: So doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe euery Chriſtian who is not ignorant, how veheme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly he is incited to ſinne by the fleſh, the world, and the diuell, and how many, and various kinds of troubles he ſuffers in this vale of miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, and to how many and how great perills and dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers of this life he is expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, is dayly forced and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelled euery moment to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire the ayd and aſſiſtance of gods diuine grace. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by he may att length freed from theſe euills fly vp to the moſt cleere ſight of God, and to the fruition of aeter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:15454:16"/>happineſſe. And this de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire is oftentimes in holy writt vnderſtood to be as a certeine crye in the eares of God, <hi>Our Lord,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Pſal. 9.</note> ſayth the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet David, <hi>hath heard the crye of the poore.</hi> For the deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re of thoſe who are troubled and afflicted doth quickly come to the prese<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of God, and makes a great crye in his eares. And becauſe in the hearts of the godly this deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re doth neuer ceaſe, but is inceſſantly moved, and ſtir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, and alwayſe ſeeketh and imploreth the diuine aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance, euen whether they are then a wake or ſleepe, or eate or drinke or what elſe ſo euer they doe, they are rightly ſayd alwayſe to
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:15454:17"/>pray and without intermiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion. Which moveth S. Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtin to ſay,<note place="margin">Epiſt. 112. c. 9. ad Dro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bam.</note> 
                     <hi>Pray yee with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out intermiſsion, what other thing doth it meane, then deſire without intermiſsion aeternel li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fe? let vs deſire this of our Lord, and we alwayſe pray.</hi> Thus S. Auguſtin: without this de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire noe muttering of words though neuer ſo prolix can open the eares of his diuine Majeſtie. But this deſire of it ſelfe if it be fervent, alt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hough there be no noyſe at all of words, doth moſt eaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie penetrate, and without any delay obteines a preſent hearing, as we ſhal declare more plainely heereafter.</p>
                  <p>Whoſoeuer therefore ſhal vnderſtand this ſaying of
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:15454:17"/>Chriſt according to this ſenſe, ſhal in my opinion rightly vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d it, neyther can wee other iſe eaſilie conceiue any man alwayſe to pray to God, and to ſpend both night and day without intermiſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in prayer: But by this <hi>deſire</hi> which in the heart of holy men is neuer extin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhed God is alwayſe and inceſſantly prayed vnto, and by it wee knoke per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuallie at the gates of his diuine mercy for the obtai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of his grace and aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance. Therefore it is moſt true which Chriſt ſayd,<note place="margin">Lu. 18.</note> 
                     <hi>we ought alwayſe to pray and not to giue ouer</hi> But not ſoe that any ſett prayer formed by words muſt alwayſe be vttered by
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:15454:18"/>vs eyther by our mouth or mind, but that no moment of time doe paſſe vs where in we doe not deſire the ayde of his grace and euerlaſting happineſſe. But becauſe we are to ſpeake ſomewhat mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re heereafter of this mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tere. Therefore we will now produce ſome reaſons, w<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hich if we ſhal diligently ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue they will both encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage vs to ſhalke of ſloath and with more diligence and and facilitie ſtirre vs vp to pray.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="chapter">
                  <pb n="19" facs="tcp:15454:18"/>
                  <head>The firſt reaſon why God is to be prayed vnto. <hi>CHAP. II.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>THis ought firſt of all to moue vs,<note place="margin">A ſimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litude.</note> that prayer is like to a certeine golden ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pe or chaine lett downe from heaven, by which we cndea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to draw God to vs whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reas in deed we are more truly drawne by him. For ſo it is as if one ſtanding in a higher place and wold draw another from below he let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth downe ſome cord or li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne vnto him, on which he laying hould, and with all his forces drawing is att laſt ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vated to the topp. This rope
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:15454:19"/>or golden Chaine holy S. Dioniſius calleth prayer,<note place="margin">Cap. 3. de di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinis nomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus.</note> which truly is let downe to vs from heauen, and by God himſelfe faſtened to our hearts: for no man truly and heartily prayes, if he be not inſpired by God,<note place="margin">2. Cor. 3.</note> 
                     <hi>Seing we are not of our ſelues,</hi> as Saint Paul ſayth, <hi>Sufficient to thinke any thing that is good, but our ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiency is of God.</hi> This line the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>refore is let downe vnto vs, that we continuallic hanging at it may att laſt be lifted vp to heauen to the fruition of God. But let vs lay open this matter yett more at large. When one conſiders deepely on the one ſide the infinite goodneſſe, pietie, and beni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gnitie of God, and on the
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:15454:19"/>other ſide his owne pouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, want, and miſeric, then is he preſently forced to ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke after the ayde, comfort and preſence of God his moſt benigne Creator and Protector, as the kingly Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet Sayth,<note place="margin">Pſalm. 26.</note> 
                     <hi>I haue ſought after thy countenance, O Lord I will ſeeke after thy countenance.</hi> And when he beleives that he is truly preſent, then he expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth and diſcouereth his mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeries and neceſſities, then he doubleth his deſires, then with many teares and ſithes he imploreth the diuine goodneſſe, that he would be graciouſlic pleaſed to helpe him in his neceſſities, and not to forſake him in theſe his afflictions, and to aſſiſt
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:15454:20"/>him with his helping grace, by wich he may in all things beſt pleaſe his diuine Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie. And whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ſoule doth this, what other thing doth it but ſeeme to be drawne vp to God by this line or cord of prayer? What els doth it but ſtriue to be ſweetly bound vnto hits Creator? What doth it, but labour to conioyne its vnderſtanding with the incomprehenſible light of his diuine Majeſtie? What cls doth it, but vnite its affections, with his vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpeakeable goodneſſe? La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtly what other thing doth it, but elevates the mind aboue all things created, ſoe that att laſt it is made one ſpirit with God, faſt bound vnto
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:15454:20"/>him with this golden line or chaine of prayer. Behold now what kind of bond this prayer is. O line more then golden! O chaine aboue all iewells to be deſired! O moſt ſweet bond of loue; who would not moſt willingly be bound with this moſt ſoft, and ſilken cord? Or laſtly who doth not deſire from the bottomè of his heart to repoſe himſelfe in the armes of ſo loving à Prince, ſo po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent a King? Verely this onely cogitation if it were deepely conſidered, might ſuffice to inflame the moſt frozen heart, and to ſtirre it vp to freque<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t this holy exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe of prayer: And the ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, for that euery one, how
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:15454:21"/>miſerable a ſinner ſo euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>he be, may, and ought with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out all queſtion to hope, that his diuine Majeſtie though incomparablie high and ſuperemine<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, yet neuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſſe is ſo loving ſoe ſweeet, and ſo mercifull, that he doth not diſdeigne to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cline his moſt ſacred eares vnto our prayers, ſo that we haue a purpoſe heereafter to reſiſt ſinne. For almightie God is ſoe willing and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſe to forgiue our ſinnes, and loueth our ſoules ſo dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rely, that though he be the ſupreme Lord Paramount, and gouernour of the world, and wee nothing but vnclea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne durt and aſhes, yet doth he not contemne our miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:15454:21"/>nor keepe in memorie our old ſinnes be they neuer ſo great; but preſently being attentine vnto our grifes, and moued with our teares, grants our deſires, and par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dons our offences: and which is more, preuents vs ſo with his grace, that wee are by him ſtirred vp to pray befo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re we beginne to pray. O in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſtimable loue of God! O in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comparable clemencie! So deepely is God almightie in loue with our ſoules, that he doth as it were ſtudie ſweetly t'intice and allure vs, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavoureth by all meanes to draw vs to meditate and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>template the ſplendor of his glory, to imbrace the large<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peſſe of his bounty, to taſt of
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:15454:22"/>his pleaſing ſweetneſſe, and laſtly to kiſſe the vnſpeakea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble delights of his mouth. O miſerable and vnhappie men, who doe not ſtriue with all theire forcesto be drawne with this ſilken cord! But more miſerable they, who doe not follow ſo ſweet a draught, but of all, moſt mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable and vnhappie are thoſe, who being ſo drawne doe wittingly refuſe, and ſpurne againſt this ineffable clemency of almightie God. And this may ſuffice for the firſt reaſon or motiue to prayer.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="chapter">
                  <pb n="27" facs="tcp:15454:22"/>
                  <head>The ſecond reaſon why God is to be prayed vnto. <hi>CHAP. III.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>BVt now let vs come to the ſecond reaſon which may edge vs to this exerciſe of prayer. It is moſt certaine that mans cheifeſt good, is beatitude, which is conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and ordeined by God as the laſt end of man. To this end no man can attaine, but by fitt meanes condu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing thereunto. And theſe (among many others) be two, which whoſoeuer hath ſhall neuer want any thing neceſſarie for the obteining of this happineſſe. Theſe two
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:15454:23"/>are prayer and good workes. In theſe two as we reade in the Acts of the Apoſtles, Cornelius the Centurion was very well exerciſed, and by them, did ſo pleaſe God, that though he were yet a heathen or Ethnicke, it was ſayd vnto him by the mouth of an Angell, <hi>Thy prayers and thy almeſdeeds haue aſcended into remembrance in ſight of God.</hi> whoſoeuer then ſhal exerci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe himſelfe wel in theſe two, that is, prayer and good wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes, ſhall not be deſtitute of any thing that may helpe him to obteine this end of his ſaluation.</p>
                  <p>But God will alſo further haue vs to hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ble our ſelues in the ſight of his diuine Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:15454:23"/>acknowledging our ſelues not to be able of our owne forces to doe any thing worthy of his acceptance: but that a good life, that is, the life of good workes is to be obteined from him by prayer, and by this meanes to come to our laſt end, which is aeternall happineſe: By cauſe therefore no man can come vnto this end with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the grace of good wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes, and man obteines not this grace but by prayer; It followeth that if we will eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cape aeternall miſerie, and poſſeſſe aeternal ioy in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven we muſt dayly exerciſe our ſelues in prayer.</p>
                  <p>Let no man here obiect vnto me that abſurd and ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diculous
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:15454:24"/>reaſon of the fore kmowledge of God, which cannot be fruſtrated or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued: God, ſay they, in his know ledge ſeeth all things ſhall be before they come to paſſe. For exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple, without all queſtion he knoweth, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther I ſhal be ſaved or ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iudged to perpetuall tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments: and if he knweth me to be ſaved, I haue no need to pray, by cauſe without any prayer of mine I ſhall be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, to wit, by vertue of his foreknowledge, which can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be deceiued: But if he knowes me to be da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ned, no prayers of myne can helpe or avayle me, ſeing Gods fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reknowledge cannot be fru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrated. This very dilemma
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:15454:24"/>hath indeed ſeduced many: But how deceipt full it is, we ſhal preſently perceiue, if we make a litle try all, how ſmall force it hath in other things: For example ſake;<note place="margin">Conue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xempes.</note> he that is ſicke of any diſſeaſe, by this reaſon ſhal take noe phiſic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke, for God knowes whether he ſhall liue or die of this infirmitie: But if he forek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowes him to liue, then he hath no neede of medicine at all, for without all que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion he ſhall recouer with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out it; for the diuine forek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>now lege ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not be deceiued: But if God foreſees that he ſhall die of this diſeaſe, no phiſike can helpe him, for that he foreſeeth ſhall be, and can by no meanes be avoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded.
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:15454:25"/>So by this reaſon you ſee, the Commodious art of phiſike is quite taken away. But let vs trye in another. The husband man may ſay, I will not plough my land, for God fore ſeeth whether it will bring forth fruit or no this next yeare: if he fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeeth that it wil bring forth fruit, it will doe it without any labour: If he know al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo it will not, my labour will be in vaine. And thus you ſee all husbandrie is to delayd aſide. And ſoe will it fall out in other things if we examine them. Thus is the weakeneſſe, and the wicked neſſe of this former diſcour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe made euident: by cauſe by it neyther the ſicke man ſhall
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:15454:25"/>take any phiſicke, nor the ploughman tille his land. Wherefore as the husband man can expect no fruit from the earth, vn leſſe he ſhall plough and ſowe the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me, nor the ſicke man expect health, vn leſſe he ſhall vſe the art of phiſicke, anh obey the preceps of the phiſitian. So no Chriſtian can euer co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me vnto aeternall happineſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe, but by leading a godly li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fe, which he cannot atteine vnto but by prayer. And we ſee by experience, that ſicke people would die, if they did not vſe the art, and follow the councell of their Doctor, and fe ilds without plowing. And good ſeede vould bring forth no fruit: Soe can we
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:15454:26"/>neyther euer thinke or ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect without prayer and good pious workesto obtaine eternall ioy, and happineſſe. For although God almightie hath ordeined this eternall beatitude for mans laſt end, yet he will not that we attai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne vnto it without the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portionable meanes which he hath appointed for it. For vnleſſe a man heere begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth a good life, lett him ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer expect the glory which is inthe other: and good life let no man looke for, vnleſſe he beggeth it att the hands of God by dayly prayer. We muſt therefore beginne with prayer, from whence pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedes good life, by which at laſt, we are brought vnto
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:15454:26"/>the heavenly glory, which is the moſt cleere viſion of al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mihtie God, of which whilſt we are deprived, we muſt needes thinke our ſelues moſt miſerable and vnhap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pie men.</p>
                  <p>And this moſt manifeſtly appeares, by the vnſatiable deſire of ovr ſoules, which never are quiet, but ſtill la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bouring and endeavouring to find out ſome thing that might ſatiate and fill vs. And this we thinke to find, ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in having riches, or pleaſures, or honours, or in all of them together; and yet it will not be. From hence proceedes that theire is ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver an end of deſiring theſe things, and for the obtei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:15454:27"/>of theſe things all good order is broken, and a gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall confuſion of all things brought into the world. Yet nothing of all theſe can ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiate our deſires, which are of ſo large an extent and ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacitie, that they cannot be ſatisfide, but with the chei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt good which is God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe. The contemplation therefore and fruition of this good, is aboue all things to be deſired, this onely ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfieth, this banisheth all longing. But this cannot be obteined but by good life, nor good life without prayer; where by it appeares that whoſoever deſires to in ioy this happineſſe, muſt cheife<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly aboue all things be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:15454:27"/>to this holy exerciſe of prayer. Thus much for the ſecond reaſon.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="chapter">
                  <head>The third reaſon why God in to be prayed vnto. <hi>CHAP. II.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>IN this third place it will not a litle ſtirre vs vp, that Chriſt Ieſus himſelfe hath warned vs with his owne mouth to be ſedulous in prayer: <hi>we ought alwayſe to pray.</hi> For who knowes bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter how to inſtruct vs in tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe things that belong to our eternal ſaluation, then the ſonne of Almightie God, in whome God the father pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced the treaſures of his wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:15454:28"/>and knowledge, and who for that purpoſe diſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded into this world, to ſhow vs the right way to our hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly countrie. Or who will endeavour with more effica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy to teach vs the way, then hee, who for the loue of vs hath vndergonne the moſt troubleſome, moſt ignomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nious, and moſt painfull and contemptible death of the Croſſe</p>
                  <p>Neyther hath he onely ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniſhed vs of the neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of praying continuallie; but he hath likewiſe promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, that we ſhall obteine any thing we deſire of him in prayer ſaying: <hi>Aske, and yee ſhall receiue, ſeeke, and yee ſhal find, knocke and is ſhall
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:15454:28"/>be opened vnto yee.</hi> This, Ieſus Chriſt the ſonne of God, who is truth it ſelfe, hath pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſed with his owne mouth. Let vs therefore flie vnto the throne of his clemency, and lett vs there continuallie pray, for the grace of good life and perſeuera<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce in good workes, nothing doubting but he wil more willingly and liberallie grant our re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſts, then we know to begg or dema<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d them at his hands.</p>
                  <p>Therefore ſeing he hath taught vs the neceſſitie of prayer, and that we ought alwayſe to pray, it cannot be doubtfull to any, but that aboue all things, it is dayly and houerly to be practiſſed; And eſpeciallie of vs Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians,
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:15454:29"/>who wander in the miſeries of this world exi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led from the face of our hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly father, it is ſo neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie for vs to obey this who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſome councell of Chriſt, that if any one ſhall deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minately reſolue with him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe not to pray, he ſinneth mortally, And which is more, whoſoeuer ſhall maliciouſly neglect to pray, having time and opportunitie, and chei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fely; when he ſeeth himſelfe in danger to fall into ſinne: ſuch negligence may like wiſe be mortall, although the negligence of its owne natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re be but a venial ſinne, grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter or leſſer according to the greatneſſe of the negli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence.</p>
                  <pb n="41" facs="tcp:15454:29"/>
                  <p>But if wee ſhall more dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently diſcuſſe the words of our Saviour, the neceſſitie of prayer will yet more mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſtly appeare. The ſaluation certeinly of euery Chriſtian depends of God, whome we muſt dayly implore for ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining of the ſame, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe this ſaluation of ours is in continual danger, and that euery one is bound to procure it with all the care and diligence he can, hence is it that euery moment, we are bound to pray to God for it, alwaiſe to lift vp our eyes to heauen, alwayſe to lift vp our hearts to God, ſeing it is not to be obteined by any other meanes then from him and by him.</p>
                  <pb n="42" facs="tcp:15454:30"/>
                  <p>Neyther muſt we onely pray for our owne ſalvation, but alſo for the ſaluation of our neighbours For as euery one is bound to ſuccour and releiue him when he ſeeth him in corporall and tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral neceſſitye: ſoe is he much more bound, when he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeeth him in any ſpirituall danger of his ſoul, to releiue him. And at this preſent ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me we haue moſt neede to pray, ſeing the times be ſuch, and ſo dangerous, as they now be, ſinners being ſo multiplied vpon the earth, and ſinne it ſelfe ſo dayly en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſed as we ſee it is. Now adayes ſinne is applauded and commended as Iuſtice, and good workes reputed
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:15454:30"/>ſinnes. Now to ſim is to doe welle, and contrary wiſe, to doe well, to ſinne. Woe be vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vs that are borne in theſe miſerable times! In which (with teares I ſpeake) who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer indureth with the zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le and feare of God, behol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth the manners and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation of the people, he will preſently be moved to greife and teares. This ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry conſideration ought iuſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to moue vs, that being humbled and truly ſorrie for our ſinnes, we should by prayer lye continuallie knoc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king at the Gates of Gods mercy and clemency, not onely for our owne ſafety, but alſo for the recouery of our neighbours, whome we
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:15454:31"/>ſee in ſo miſerable and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treame danger of theire ſouls, from whence they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ariſe, but by continuall prayer, and imploring of Gods diuine aſſiſtance.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="chapter">
                  <head>The fourth and laſt reaſon why God ought to be prayed vnto. <hi>CHAP. V.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>THe fourth and laſt rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon may be gathered af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter this manner. There is noe man, clothed with this mortall flesh, who hath not ſometimes finned, and high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly offended the Maieſtie of God, nor that hath any war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant or ſecuritie, heereaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:15454:31"/>not to ſinne. And in this reſpect it is moſt neceſſary for vs by dayly prayer, not onely to ſeeke, that he would graciouſly pardon and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giue our former ſinnes: But alſo that he would be plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to prevent vs with his grace, leſt we fall againe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to other ſinnes, through which we may incurre eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal punishment.</p>
                  <p>And firſt there is no man whoſe ſoul hath once been infected with ſinne, that cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teinly knowes, whether he be in the grace of God or noe, vnleſſe it be reuealed vnto him. Wherefore Salo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon ſayth in his booke of Eccleſiaſtes <hi>There be iuſt, and wiſe men and theire workes
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:15454:32"/>be in the hands of God, and yet man knoweth not whether he be worthy of loue or hatred, but all things are kept vncertaine vnto the laſt,</hi> that is, all things are left to the laſt examine, where nothing shall be hid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den, not the leaſt thought that hath entered into mans herat shalbe concealed from the moſt ſtrict iudge.</p>
                  <p>But, although no man in this eſtate of life knowes certeinty whether he be in ſtate of grace or noe, yet by certeine coniectures he may vndoubtedly beleeue it: and eſpeciallie, when he knowes not that his conſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cience is charged with any mortall ſinne, of which he hath not heere to fore repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted,
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:15454:32"/>or which he hath not diſcouered to his ghoſtly fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, or doth intend to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couer at his firſt opportuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie: And if moreouer he finds himſelfe inclined to doe and put in execution, thoſe things which belong to the honour of God, if he be delighted to heare holy ſcriptures, to be often pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent at diuine ſeruice, and be reſolute by Gods gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce, ſo much as is in his po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer to abſteine from all con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tagion of ſinne. This man doubtleſſe may belecue that he is in the ſtate of grace, but as I ſayd before, no man can certeinly know this, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe he be ſpeciallie illumi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nated from aboue. And for
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:15454:33"/>this cauſe it is neceſſarie for all men to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>teine them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues within the limitts and bounds of feare, and to be perſeuerantly knocking at the gates of gods mercy. To this feare doth the holy ſcripture perſwade vs ſaying <hi>Be not without feare of the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giueneſſe of thy ſinns.</hi> And tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly this feare will ſo much helpe and avayle vs, that if the greife before taken for our ſinns were not ſufficient, Almightie god now appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing of this feare, and wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hall accepting of the prayer, which this feare begetteth, it wil ſatisfie Gods wroth, and obteine mercy and par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don of all his ſinnes before committed.</p>
                  <pb n="49" facs="tcp:15454:33"/>
                  <p>Moreouer if we grant the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re be any man that knowes he hath full remiſſion of all his ſinnes, and that he be wholy reconciled to God, and certeinly in his grace: yet may ſuch an one very well doubt, whether he may not fall from this ſo happie an eſtate; ſeing that there is no man ſo confirmed in grace, but that he may fall from it: wherefore S. Paul giues this councell to the Romans: <hi>Thouſtandeſt by fay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>th,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Ro. 11.</note> 
                     <hi>be not Onerwiſe but feare</hi> as if he should ſay, if tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough fayth any one be in ſtate of grace, let him not therefore preſume of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, but let him rather fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re, ſeing he may ſo eaſily
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:15454:34"/>fall. No man can be ſecure in this world as S. Paul li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kewiſe ſayth to the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinthians: <hi>He that thinketh himſelfe to ſtand,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">2. Cor. 10.</note> 
                     <hi>lett him take heed he fals not.</hi> Wherefore it is moſt neceſſarie for vs to lift vp our eyes and hands to heaven, and with moſt humble &amp; heartie prayers to intreate of God, to grant vs the grace of perſeverance; leaſt we fal from this happie eſtate we are in by his grace: For we reade of many; whoe haue ſtood vp like pillers a long time in the Church of Chriſt, and haue shined like as burning lamps of ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, yet becauſe they haue not conteined themſelues within the limitts of this
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:15454:34"/>humble feare, they haue fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len headlong into the bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tomeleſſe pitt of hell, not onely to their owne ruine and infamie but the ruine of many others, which, here but that I feare to be te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious, I could confirme by the authoritie of holy do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors, and indubitable hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtories of the Church.</p>
                  <p>Now out of this we haue heere ſayd, it appeares to euery man that <hi>we ought al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayſe to pray,</hi> as well for the obteining pardon of our ſinns, as alſo to avoyde the imminent dangers we may ſo eaſily fall into. And thus having treated of theſe foure reaſons, ſo much (I hope.) as is ſufficient, I will
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:15454:35"/>now ſpeake ſomething of the fruit of prayer which I promiſed to doe in this ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond part.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <pb n="53" facs="tcp:15454:35"/>
               <head>THE SECOND, PART OF THE THREE CHEIFE FRVITS of prayer.</head>
               <div n="1" type="chapter">
                  <head>CHAPT. I.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>LTHOVGH the a foreſayd reaſons may ſeeme more then ſufficient to ſtirre vp mens minds vnto prayer, yet not with ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding there be many very slow and dull to this exerciſe, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe forſoth they doe not
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:15454:36"/>taſt that inward ſweetneſſe, which many devout ſouls doe oftentimes find in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues. They would willing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, they ſay, pray, if they could in ioy that ſuch inward comfort and content, which others doe. But withall they then doe not conſider, that prayer muſt goe before, and ſwetneſſe and delight will come after. For as in the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die by long motion and agi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of it, heate comes and increaſeth, euen ſo by long vſe and perſeuerance in prayer, begineth and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſſeth that ſweetneſſe and comfort in the ſoul, which is moſt pleaſant and aboue all meſaure comfortable. And although euery one taſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:15454:36"/>not this ſweetneſſe in prayer; yet there be other fruits which we reape by praying, which be of three ſorts. The firſt is the meritt it ſelfe, which God hath pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed to giue vnto vs for praying. The ſecond is the obteining of the thing we pray for. The third is the taſt of that wonderfull ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, which we find in our ſelfes in the time of prayer. Which three kind of fruits, are ſo different in themſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues, that one may attaine vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the firſt without the other two. For one may by prayer meritt, yet not obteine that which he prayeth for as ſaint Paul did, whoe ſayth that,<note place="margin">2. Cor. 12.</note> 
                     <hi>He prayed to God three times
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:15454:37"/>that the ſting of the fleshe;</hi> with which he was very much troubled <hi>might be taken from him.</hi> Yet he did not obteine what he prayed for, but for all this, it is moſt certeine he did not looſe the meritt of his prayer. And the two firſt may be obteined without the third, which queſtion<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe dayly happens vnto ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, who begging pardon of their ſinns, doe obteine it, and beſides this, they are not fruſtrated of the meritt of prayer, yet theyare not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freshed with that inward ioy and ſpirituall ſweetneſſe. For the Publican, which Chriſt ſpeaketh of in the ghoſpel, when he begged pardon of his ſinns ſaying,
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:15454:37"/>
                     <hi>God haue mercy on me a ſinner,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Mart. 18.</note> obteined bothe the meritt of his prayer, and the forgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veneſſe of his ſinns, for it followeth in the ghoſpell,<note place="margin">Ibid.</note> 
                     <hi>He went away iuſtified into his ow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne bowſe.</hi> But we doe not rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de that he receiued any ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall ſweetneſſe or delight in his ſoul. Whereby it is moſt apparant that theſe three fruits are ſo different. that happen not all to euery one. But that we may more eleerely fee the excellency of each of them we will treat of them in order apart, and firſt of the meritt of prayer.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="chapter">
                  <pb n="58" facs="tcp:15454:38"/>
                  <head>Of the firſt fruit of Prayer that is of the meritt. <hi>CHAP. II.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>VVe haue before ſayd that meritt is the firſt fruit of prayer, which we will not haue vnderſtood of any meritt, but of that one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to which a reward in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven doth correſpond, and is due, which diuines call eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentiall. For it is certeine,<note place="margin">Vvicked man ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue ſome meritt of their prayers.</note> that there is no man, with how great ſinns ſocuer he be charged, that ſhal be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prived of all meritt of his prayer: for he ſhall eyther be rewarded in this world with ſome temporall reward, or at
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:15454:38"/>beſt his paines ſhalbe ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what mittigated in the next, but in reſpect of ſuch prayer, he ſhall neuer obteine any the Ieaſt portion of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly glory, for that is not obteined by any, but thoſe, whoſe prayer ſpringeth from the roote of charitie, that is, who are in the ſtate of grace when they pray.</p>
                  <p>Whoſoeuer therefore deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth not to be depriued of this meritt, muſt firſt indea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to haue charitie deepe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly planted and rooted in his heart: and ſo, not onely his prayer, but all his workes ſhalbe meritorious. And the greater that the charitie is, the more meritorius will the worke be, whence I gather
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:15454:39"/>that they meritt moſt,<note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> prayer is moſt me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritorious</note> who heartily pray for their eni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, becauſe that kind of prayer proceedes from the higheſt degree of charitie. And therefore it is requiſite for euery one that will inioy the benefitt of his prayer, that he indeavour by all meanes not to want charitie, that is, that be be in the ſtate of grace.<note place="margin">In 105.</note> Which ſaint Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoſtome vpon the ghoſpell of ſaint Iohn doth affirme to be a very eaſie thing, euen for him whoe is laden with great ſinns. Onely lett him heartily repent him of his finns, and reſolue to leade a new life in Chriſt, to get his grace. Which ſaying is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed by the Prophet Eze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiell,
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:15454:39"/>whoe from the mouth of God almightie promiſeth,<note place="margin">Ezech. 33.</note> that <hi>In what houre ſoeuer a ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner ſhal repent, all his iniquities ſhalbe forgotten I will not ſayth he remember all his iniquities:</hi> But ſinns are not thought to be blotted out of the memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie of God by any other way then by the gift and infuſion of grace and charitie. By which meanes it comes to paſſe, that a ſinner whoe giues ouer ſinning, that is, whoe is truly ſorrowfull for his former life, and is beco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me obedient to Chriſt, is eſteemed to be in the ſtate of grace and charitie. And for ſo much as the leaving of our former ſinns, and changing our old life depe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deth partly
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:15454:40" rendition="simple:additions"/>of our owne free will, which is free to euery man, and life dependeth partly of the hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pe of diuine grace, which is wanting to no man, that is not wanting to himſelfe, it is not very hard for a ſinner in a ſhort time to become a iuſt man, ſo that he effectuallie deſires it, and haue a great co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fidence in almightie God. Who ſo then goeing about to pray, renewes his fayth in Chriſt Ieſus, by a new act, and deteſteth the impuritie of his former life, and reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth heereafter to abſteine from ſinne, and to doe ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the decrees and ordinances of the Church, without all queſtion, ſuch an one is in the ſtate of grace
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:15454:40"/>and charitie, and ſhal not be fruſtrated of this fruit of his prayer, that is of ſuch meritt to which a reward in the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of heauen belongeth. And thus much of the firſt fruit of prayer.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="chapter">
                  <head>Of the ſecond fruit Which is the obtaining of the thing We pray for. <hi>CHAP. III.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>THe ſecond fruit we ſayd to be the obteining of the thing we aſke in prayer. This fruit whoſoeuer will inioy, it is not ſufficient for him that he be in charitie, alſo he muſt ſtand firmely vpon the foundation of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>found
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:15454:41"/>humilitie,<note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>evo prayer may be impetra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory.</note> ſo that from the bottome of his hart he muſt thincke himſelfe moſt vnworthie that God should beſtow vpon him any grace or benefit, or inſpire him with any good at all. And yet let him not ceaſe ſtill to thanke god for what he hath alreadie receiued, attributing nothing to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, if any thing be well donne, but referring all to God, what he hath donne good, and to himſelfe all that is evill.<note place="margin">A ſimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litude.</note> For ſo oft as we doe any thing well, we are in the hands of God, as the mallett is in the hande of the carpenter, and as one shold ſay as the carpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter in working vſeth the
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:15454:41"/>mallet as an inſtrument, even ſo doth almightie God vſe vs as his inſtruments, ſo oft as we doe any thing well. For whatſoeuer ſeemes to be well donne by vs, it is not wee of our ſelues, but God that worketh in vs. wherefore as the mallet cannot boaſt it ſelfe againſt the carpenter, nor aſcribe vnto it ſelfe, that it hath framed this or that worke (for the hammer or mallet doth nothing of it ſelfe,<note place="margin">Ro. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </note> but the carpenter that worketh with it as his inſtrument.) So likewiſe it is not lawfull for vs to ſay againſt God, or to thinke, that we of our ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues or by our owne forces onely, haue do<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne theſe good
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:15454:42"/>workes, but by the aſſiſtance of Gods grace, by which he moues vs, and by vs as by his inſtruments produceth good workes. Wherefore we ought with all the humilitie we can to render thankes vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to God who hath vouchſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fed graciouſly to vſe vs as his inſtruments, when (if it had ſo pleaſed his goodneſſe and benignitie) he might haue vſed others, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happs with ſo much more fruit, by how much they ſhould haue better coopera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with his grace, then we haue donne.</p>
                  <p>And when one by this conſideration hath humbled himſelfe in the ſight of his diuine Majeſtie; yet muſt he
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:15454:42"/>further diligently examine whether that which he is about to pray for, be againſt his ſouls health or not, if it be, he muſt not expect to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teine any ſuch thing att the hands of God. For God, being of his owne nature moſt good, moſt bountifull, cannot grant vnto his peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiones, that which he knowes to be pernitious, and hurt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full vnto him. And he kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weth long before we demand it, whether it will damnifie or proffit vs. Hence it is that we doe not preſently obtei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne that which we aſke for, be cauſe God ſeeth it will be a hinderance to our ſoule.</p>
                  <p>But there is yet a third thing required to the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teining
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:15454:43"/>of this fruit of pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yer, that is,<note place="margin">Vve ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teine not for others as for our ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues</note> that it concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes our ſelues that we pray for: For although we be bound to pray for our ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ighbours, yet are we not alwayſe heard, praying for them, eſpeciallie for ſo much as apparteines to this fruit. For perchance eyt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>her they are not worthy to haue that granted vnto them that we pray for, or perhap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ps it is not profitable for theire ſouls health.</p>
                  <p>And in caſe we doe not obteine the thing for whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ch we pray; yet shall not our prayer be in vaine and fruſtrate of all reward: for he whoe prayeth for his ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ighbour, and obteiyneth
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:15454:43"/>not for him, yet he meri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth for himſelfe, <hi>My pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yer</hi> ſaythe the prophet, <hi>shall be turned into my owne boſome:</hi> as if he had ſayd, my pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yer when I praye for others,<note place="margin">Pſalm 34.</note> if it profiteth them not, yet shall it not want its reward, becauſe I know it will be turned to my good, the prof<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitt will redound to me, it will be turned into my owne boſome with advantage.</p>
                  <p>If therefore the prayer of any one be grounded vpon this profound humilitie,<note place="margin">Three things requiſit that o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> prayer be imp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erator</note> and for himſelfe, and deman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding nothing preiuditiall to his ſouls health; let him pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceede in Gods name whoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer he be, not doubting but that he shall obtein what
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:15454:44"/>he prayeth for, not doub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting I ſay, be cauſe ſaint Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes promiſeth ſaying <hi>let him aske in fayth, nothing doub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting and it shalbe granted vnto him.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Iac. 1.</note> And our lord alſo in the goſpell ſayth <hi>what ſocuer praying yee shall aske, beleiue that yee shall receiue, and it shall be donne vnto yee:</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Marc. 11.</note> And let this ſuffice concerning the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond fruit of prayer and how we may atteine vnto it.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="chapter">
                  <head>Of the third fruit of prayer which is ſpirituall ſweetneſſe <hi>CHAP. IIII.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>THe third fruit of prayer we haue ſayd to be a
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:15454:44"/>certeine Spirituall ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, with which our ſoule is marvelouſly affected and deligheted in praying. Of this fruit whoſoeuer deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth to taſt and to be perta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker off, it is not ſufficient for him to haue charitie, and humilitie, and the other things aboue rehearſed: but he muſt alſo haue a vehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment attention vnto the pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yer he hath in hand, and not to ſuffer his mind to wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der abroad at all.</p>
                  <p>And although attention be moſt neceſſarie to euery one who deſires to atteine vnto the two former fruites aboue here mentioned,<note place="margin">Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinual attetion neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                           <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                        </gap>.</note> that is meritt, and the gayning of the thing we pray for; yet
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:15454:45"/>neuertheleſſe it will ſuffice to the gaigning of them, if in the beginning of our prayer, the mind be truly ſetled and attentiue, ſoe that we ſuffer it not willfullie afterwards to wander: for though after out of humane weakeneſſe and frayltie one be ſome what diſtracted, or grow cold tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough ſome ſmall negligence and forgetfulneſſe; he ſhall not yet looſe the benefitt of his prayer, but by vertue of his firſt inte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tion, gaigne both the meritt of his prayer and the thing ſo prayed for, which may eaſily be made apparent by this example. If aman hath a mind to throw a ſtone to any diſtant place,<note place="margin">A ſimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litude</note> it is not neceſſarie that the
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:15454:45"/>hand of him that caſt eth the ſtone ſhould ſtill be ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried with the ſtone, but the firſt vertue or force, which the thrower impreſſed into it, wil be ſufficient to convey it to the place intended. E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen ſo its with him that goeth to pray to almightie God: it is ſufficient for him, if at the beginninge he be very at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentiue, and haue a deſire and good will ſo to continue vnto the end. For though his mind be a litle afte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rwards caried away, yet ſhall he not want eyther of the two former fruits.</p>
                  <p>But he that will inioy this third fruit, to wit, be refreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hed with the conſolation of this ſpirituall ſweetneſſe, it
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:15454:46"/>is not ſufficie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t for him when he beginneth firſt to pray, to be attentiue and recollected, but he muſt perſeuere ſo to the end, not ſuffering his mind to be diſtracted or ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried away, but ſtill directing it, with all poſſible care, to him, to whome he prayeth. Wherefore it is fitting for him who deſires to taſt this ſpirituall ſweetneſſe in prayer,<note place="margin">The vvay to atteine vnto ſvvei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe in prayer.</note> before he beginneth his prayer to caſt out of his mind all idle and vaine cogi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, and diligently to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare his mind, and with all the ſtrength he may, to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect all his intentions to al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mightie God, leaſt thorough his negligence in ſucceſſe of prayer, he be tranſpor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted,
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:15454:46" rendition="simple:additions"/>and his intention loſt by diſtraction. Wherefore the Ancient indued with great vertue and ſanctite of life, ſo oft as they went to pray, ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>died and indeavoured by all meanes ſtirre to them ſelues vp to deuotion, ſome times Kneeling downe, ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me times lying proſtrate on the earth, now with exten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded armes in forme of a Croſſe, now lifting theire hands vp to heaven, ſometi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes ſitting ſolitarie, muſing and full of thoughts, ſweetly conferring and talking with God, and preſently againe deuoutly ſinging ſome pſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me, canticle or himne. By theſe and many other mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, as ſeemed fitteſt for
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:15454:47"/>themſelues they were accuſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>omed wonderfullie and moſt efficatiouſly to ſtirre vp them ſelues ſoe to deuotion and contemplation, ſo farre that they ofte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> found in them ſelues, ſuch an inexplicable and delicate ſweetneſſe as no tongue is able to expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe. For indeede one only taſt of this ſweetneſſe, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comparably ſurpaſſeth all worldly delight whatſoeuer, for from it there groweth ſuch ioy and comfort in the ſoule that exceedes all ioy and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t that ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> be ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gined. And no mervaile, for it proceedes from the very fountaine of all goodneſſe, to which no worldly ioy or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light may be compared. For
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:15454:47"/>it is God himſelfe, who very often by a ſpeciall grace shewes himſelfe preſent to thoſe that devoutly contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plates him. By which it co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes to paſſe, that ſo ſoone as this moſt excellent good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe doth relish in our ſpirit or mind, forth with an admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable ſweetneſſe is diffuſed through our ſoule, ſo much ſurpaſſing al humane cogita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that mortall tongue is not able to expreſſe, or vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding to apprehend it. But this ſweetneſſe is not vſuallie att all times nor by all perſons perceived and ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted, but then onely, when almigtie God doth ſee it will be moſt profitable vnto vs. For as the phiſitian doth not
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:15454:48"/>alwayſe giue phiſicke,<note place="margin">A ſimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieude.</note> nor ſo oft as the patient deſires it, but doth ſome time deferre it to a time more fitting and commodious for his patient, and when it will doe more good. Euen ſoe doth our moſt benigne God with vs. For he doth oftentimes de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferre to giue vs this ſpirituall conſolation till a fitt time, when he knowes that the guift of this ſweetneſſe will bring more proffitt, or be more conuenient for our ſouls good.</p>
                  <p>And this is the reaſon why many,<note place="margin">Vv by vve doe not alvv ayſe ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teine his ſovvet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</note> although they dayly and heartilie pray to God, that they may be refreshed with this heavenly ſweetneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe, obteine it not ſo ſoone as
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:15454:48"/>they deſire, be cauſe God as a skilful and learned phiſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tian, expects his owne time and a fitter opportunitie. For peraduenture he ſeethe now, that if he should grant our deſire, we would grow proud, or beleeve we can ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teine his grace whenſoever we pleaſe; and by our owne forces and ſtrength. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore doth he in his diuine wiſedome, deferre the gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of our requeſt, vntill he ſeeth our heart more hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled, and better confirmed in good purpoſes, and laſtly more diligently addicted to holy exerciſes, that ſoe he may make vs pertakers of more ample fauours of his diuine ſweetneſſe and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolation.</p>
                  <pb n="80" facs="tcp:15454:49"/>
                  <p>In ſumme therefore who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer deſires to be pertaker of this ſweetneſſe muſt firſt and aboue all haue a moſt lowly and humble conceipt of himfelfe,<note place="margin">The mea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes by vvhich this ſvv<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cetneſſe is gotten.</note> 
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> that he is not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hing at all in the ſight of God, and eſteeme himſelfe to be of noe accompt, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together vnworthy not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly vpon whome almightie God ſhould beſtow a taſt of this vnſpeake able ſweetneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe, but alſo vn worhly of the very leaſt giuft att his hands, vnworthie of the meate he is fedd withall, and the very earth on which he treads.<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> He muſt further hold a ſtrong guard vpon his tongue, ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke ſparingly, rather keepe ſilence, then exerciſe the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertie
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:15454:49"/>of language, vnleſſe charitie vrgeth, neceſſitie inforceth, or that ſome com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moditie will probablie re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dound, eyther to himſelfe, or to his neighbour by ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king. Moreouer he muſt en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour ſo much as in him lyeth,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> to be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinuallie mind full of God, imagining him to be continually preſent, and to behold his actions whatſoeuer he goeth about. Lett him laſtly haue in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuall memorie the Incar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of Chriſt, the proceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe of his life, his Paſſion, and his death.<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> Lett him often meditate of the heavenly glory, which the Angells, and bleſſed ſoules now in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioy, abandoning from his
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:15454:50"/>thoughts ſo much as in him lyeth all vaine and fruitleſſe cogitations. Alas poore mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable wretches that we are, that for the moſt part peſterr our thoughts and mind (that moſt admirable creature of God) not only with ſuch fruitleſſe and vnprofitable thoughts, but with ſuch as are moſt odious, and bring damnation to our ſoules, whereas the memorie of thoſe things we ſpake of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore; were an imployment farre more adua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tagious and profitable for vs, farre more pleaſant, and the moſt excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent ſtudie that mortall man can enterteine himſelfe with. For it is as it were a twinkling or a ſmall glimps
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:15454:50"/>of Gods heavenly light, it is a ſparke of our future happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, it is a pledge or ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt penny of eternall life. And if any man in this dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing life may be termed hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pie and bleſſed, it is onely he whoe hath his mind con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſant in the memorie of theſe holy thoughts, it is he who wholy giues himſelfe to prayer and contemplation. But having as I hope, ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken ſufficiently of the three fruits of prayer, I will now att length come to treate of the manner of prayer.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:15454:51"/>
               <pb n="85" facs="tcp:15454:51"/>
               <head>THE THIRD PART, OF THE MANNER OF PRAYER.</head>
               <div n="1" type="chapter">
                  <head>CHAP. I.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T will not be very hard for vs to know which way of prayer is moſt proffitable, if the three things wee pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently shall treat of be once rightly vnderſtood. The firſt is,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> to what thing we should cheifely be attentiue in
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:15454:52"/>our prayer, whether to the words, or to the ſenſe of the words, or whither rather to him to whome we powre forth our prayers.<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> The ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond is how long or short a time it is conuenient for vs to ſpend in prayer, to witt, whether we should make long or shòrt prayers.<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> The third and laſt is, whether to pray in mind onely, or to pray both in mind and ſpeech be more availeable to our ſoule, and more accepta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to God, which three wayes, when we haue exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, it will eaſilie appeare which is the moſt excellent, and to be preferred before the reſt. Wherefore we will a part ſpeake ſome thing of
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:15454:52"/>each of them, that is, of attention, of prolixitie or length, and of pronuntia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="chapter">
                  <head>To what thing we ought cheifely to attend when we pray. <hi>CHAP. II.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>LEt vs now examine whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the force of our in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention is to be directed, whether to the words, or to the ſenſe, or rather to him whome we pray. And firſt of all I affirme that if there be any man of ſuch dexteritie in praying, that he can at one and the ſame time attend vnto them all together, ſo that his attention to the
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:15454:53"/>words, or to the ſenſe of the words, diminisheth nothing of the attention of his mind to God: that way of prayer is moſt powerfull.<note place="margin">One at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentïon commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dereth another.</note> But be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it cannot be, or very hardly, but that one of theſe attentions muſt needs hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the other, let vs perticu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly ſee which of the three is moſt perfect. No man (who will diligently examine this buſineſſe) can doubt, but the attention which is derected vnto God conſidered in it ſelfe is the moſt perfect, and that moſt meritorious, that is, if it be not more remiſſe, then that which is directed to the words, or the ſenſe of the words before God. And this I will not haue vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood,
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:15454:53"/>in thoſe prayers only which we voluntarily ſay and of our owne accord, but in all others, euen thoſe to wich we are bound, eyther by wow, or by the conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the Church.</p>
                  <p>There be many doubtleſſe whoe haue ſo weake and ſcrupulous conſciences, that for feare leaſt they should overſlipp any litle word, or paſſe any ſillable in the diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne office, they bend all their forces and ſtrength of their mind to the diſtinct pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuntiation of the words. And ſuch I doe verily belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue doe ſeldome or never taſt the ſweetneſſ of prayer, for which the ancient fathers firſt ordained the diuine of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice,
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:15454:54"/>which we call the cano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicall howres.<note place="margin">Vvhy the canoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res vvere enſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted.</note> For theſe an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient and holy men had this theire prefixed end, and it was theire ſtudie and inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that the minds of the Preiſts (who are the media<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors betwixt God and the people) should by theſe offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, be more ſtirred vp to the contemplation of God, and be more inflamed with his love. Wherefore if any one shalbe ſo farre forth at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentiue, to expreſſe his words, that he doth not co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me vnto the end and ſcope, which thoſe holy fathers propoſed vnto them ſelues in theiſe diuine offices, I ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>notapproue of ſuch prayer as the beſt, or iudge it more
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:15454:54"/>fruitfull or meritorious then the other.</p>
                  <p>But I would not heere by, that thoſe, who ſo haſtily huddle ouer theire prayer, that they ſcarſely vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d themſelues, not conſidering eyther the excelle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cy of him to whome they pray, nor the ſenſe of the words: I would not I ſay, that by theſe my words ſuch negligent people should pretend vnto them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues any the leaſt defence of theire ſloath and negli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence. For I doe not ſpeake this with any intention to condemne them,<note place="margin">Atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to the vvords ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiethe precept.</note> whoſe at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentions are tranſported to the words, (becauſe I doubt not but that they ſatisfie the precèpt) but rather to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:15454:55"/>them to the other way of prayer, which is more ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent and more proffitable.</p>
                  <p>But they who cheifly at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to the ſenſe of the words, may ſometimes per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happs receiue ſome litle ſweetneſſe, and ſpirituall comfort in their ſouls: But ſurely they doe not receiue that moſt excellent comfort and ſweetneſſe which ariſeth from the vnion and coniun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of our ſoules with God For it may ſometimes alſo happen,<note place="margin">The ſvveet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe vvhich comes from the ſenſe of the vvords is farre leſſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that comes by a thought vpon God.</note> that by one plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing ſentence of holy ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, being deepely rumi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nated, one may atteine vnto ſome ſmall ſparkle of this moſt excellent ſweetneſſe: but that which proceeds out
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:15454:55" rendition="simple:additions"/>of the conſideration of any part of ſcripture, is farre more weake, farre more re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſe, then that which pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedes from the fountaine it ſelfe of his divinitie. For Gods holy writt though it proceedes from himſelfe, yett it is notwithſtanding à creature, and what crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, or what created thing ſoeuer poſſeſſeth our minds, be it neuer ſo excellent, that thing is interpoſed betwixt God and vs, ſo that it is but a lett vnto our minds, that we cannot ſo in wardly be vnited with God, and therefore deminisheth that admirable ſweetneſſe which proceedes fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that fountaine it ſelfe wherefore although
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:15454:56"/>they who attend onely to the ſenſe of the words perceiue or find a litle ſweetneſſe, yet are they farre short of that pure ſweetneſſe which thoſe onely taſt, who thinke of nothing but God himſelfe and haue nothing interpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed betwixt God and their minds, but are vnited who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to him, which can neuer be, vnleſſe the mind relin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quish the cogitation of eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry imaginable thing or fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taſie, and preſenteth nothing to it ſelfe but God only, for then are we moſt perfectly vnited and immediatly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyned to our heave<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor. To whome when we find our harts ſo to adhere, and be as it were firmely fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xed,
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:15454:56"/>preſently beginneth ſoe pleaſant a taſt of ſweetneſſe, as no man can expreſſe, but he only to whome it hath pleaſed almightie God to grant it.</p>
                  <p>But obſerue this, that that thought or cogitation which the mind formeth or sha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peth to it ſelfe of God, muſt not be vnder any colour or light or figure or any other corporal likeneſſe: for all theſe things are created and ſo not God, whereas we ſeeke the vnion and coniun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of our ſelues with God only, and not with any ot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>her thing diſtinct from him.</p>
                  <p>If therefore one goeth ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out to thinke of God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, let him with his vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:15454:57"/>flie aboue all things created,<note place="margin">Hovv vvemay atteine to the concei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving of God a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone.</note> conceiueing in his mind a thing moſt high, moſt excellent, and by infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite degrees ſurpaſſing all other things imaginable. This if he can doe without the apprehenſion of anie light, colour, figure or like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, as I ſayd before, then hath he apprehended God himſelfe. In which affaire if thou wilt continue and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligently imploy thy ſelfe, thou shalt at laſt atteine to that vnſpeakable ſweet neſs and withall obteine the three fould fruit of thy prayer.</p>
                  <p>But if in the beginning this way ſeeme difficult to any one,<note place="margin">The medita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manitie of Chriſt leadeth to higher contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plation of God.</note> let him firſt exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe himſelfe in thinking
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:15454:57"/>vpon Ieſus Chriſt, who is both true God and true man; let him therefore fix the eye of his vnderſtanding vpon him as true God, cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to remembrance his holy Incarnation, birth, painfull labours and cruel death: Let him conſider li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kewiſe his heavenly glory, where with he now shineth, ſitting att the right hand of his father. Whoſoever shall diligently exerciſe himſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fe in theſe or any other meditation of Chriſt. Or more proportionable for him, shall eaſily from his moſt ſacred humanitie, mount to the contemplation of the moſt vnſpeakeable inſcrutable diuine Majeſtie
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:15454:58" rendition="simple:additions"/>of God. For this is the nec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt way that leadeth vs to the taſt of that moſt pure and diuine ſweetneſſe.</p>
                  <p>And if perchance he can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not yet atteine vnto this in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward comfort and ſweetneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe, almightie God withdra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wing himſelfe, eyther be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe as yet, he ſeeth it will but litle proffitt him, or becauſe he is not fervent enough, or ſufficie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue, conſidering the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and dignitie of the thing he deſires, yet for all this he shall not looſe the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward of his prayer.</p>
                  <p>The beſt therefore and moſt pure way of prayer is,<note place="margin">The moſt perfect vvay of prayer.</note> if one after he hath moſt ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly recollected himſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fe,
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:15454:58" rendition="simple:additions"/>and directed his mind with all his force vnto God himſelfe, (who is verely the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re preſent) doth offer vnto him from the bottome of his heart, and with a pure affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction; the prayers which he is about to ſay, whether he vnderſtand them or not, it is not materiall, and shal ſoe fix his mind vpon God, that his imagination wa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ders not: Such an one shal proffit mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re in the love of God (which is the end of prayer) then if he were never ſo attentiue to the words, or ſenſe of them. For this ſetling of his mind vpon God, is for the moſt part accompanied with ſuch an eleuation of heart that, the mind, having forgotten
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:15454:59" rendition="simple:additions"/>all earthly things, many ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes knoweth not where it is, or what it doth, as if a man were become a meere ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger to himſelfe; and the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit is ſometimes ſoe greatly moved, that vnadviſedly it cryes out, or doth ſome other action, which imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately after a man remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers not, becauſe the ſpiritt worketh ſo mightily in him, that he can by no meanes ſuppreſſe thoſe actions in himſelfe. And as the holy fathers (whoe in this art we<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re very expert and ſkilfull) affirme, there is oftentimes ſo great ſweetneſſe taſted in prayer, that it even redoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth to the flesh, ſo that the flesh is made pertaker of
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:15454:59" rendition="simple:additions"/>ſo great ſweetneſſe, and ſuch as it never taſted befo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re. To which the Prophet David accordeth ſaying, <hi>My heart and flesh have exul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in the living God,</hi> as if he should ſay, my heart through the bounteous overflowing of my ſpirit, hath received ſo wonderfull a ſweetneſſe from God, that my very flesh through delight of it is over come with ioy, and ſuch, as I am not able to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>teine my ſelfe. This very exultation is as it were a ſparkle of eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall life, which we shall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioy after the vniucrſall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurection of our bodies, for then the glory of the ſoule shall ſo exceedingly abou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, that it shall flow into the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die,
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:15454:60" rendition="simple:additions"/>and both ſoule and bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die with this abunda<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce shal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>be fullie ſatisfied.</p>
                  <p>Out of what hath heere bee<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſayd before in this chapter it may eaſily be gathered, that the cheifeſt attention to be vſed in prayer is to have continuallie in our memorie the preſence of God, to w<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hom we pray, and to fix him immoueablie before the eyes of our heart: which to doe, though in the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of this exerciſe, it be ſome what difficult and trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſome, yet by ſucceſſe of time and vſe of prayer, it will become more eaſie and more pleaſant: but to them cheifely, whoe are moſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flamed with the ſpirit of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uotion
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:15454:60" rendition="simple:additions"/>and contemplation. Now let vs paſſe to the next queſtion</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="chapter">
                  <head>How long our prayer ought to be. <hi>CHAPT. III.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>NOw in the ſecond pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce we muſt inquire how long our prayer ought to be, for being it may be longer or shorter as we plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe, therefore to know of what length or how short it muſt be, belongeth to the manner of prayer. I ſay therefore, that although Ieſus Chriſt admonisheth vs <hi>alwayſe to pray:</hi> it is not ſo to be vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood (as we have declared in the firſt chapter) that we
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:15454:61"/>ought alwayſe actuallie to pray, for no man is able ſo to continue, our weakeneſſe and frailtie being ſuch: that it will not permitt vs to be ſtill intent eyther to vocall or mentall prayer, without any intermiſſion: yet no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twithſtanding doth Chriſt admonish vs rightly, for that we are in continuall neede of Gods aide and aſſiſtance, which we muſt continuallie begge and intreate at his hands.</p>
                  <p>It hath pleaſed therefore ſome grave Authors to giue vs this rule, that we ſhould ſo farre prolong our prayer,<note place="margin">A ſimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litude</note> vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till we have atteined the end for which it was firſt inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted. For as the phiſitian ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plieth
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:15454:61"/>no greater or ſtron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger medecine to his pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient, then will ſerve to cure his diſeaſe, which is the end of the art of phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicke: Even ſoe muſt our prayer be, ſoe long till wee have atteined to the imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diate end for which it was inſtituted. But the firſt, and cheifeſt end of prayer is the fervor of charitie, which is the healh of our ſoules. It is fervor then of charitie that God requireth of vs, for he doth deſpiſe the lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kewarme, and in the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>calyps he preferrethe the key cold before him ſaying, <hi>I would thou wert hot or cold,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Apoc. 9.</note> 
                     <hi>but by cauſe thou art luke-arme, I will beginne to vomitt thee out of my
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:15454:62"/>mouth,</hi> See heere in how great hatred almightie God hath thoſe that are luke-warme. Wherefore we muſt labour by all meanes poſſible to procure in our ſelves this feruency of charitie. For the obteining of which fervour, prayer is of all things moſt neceſſarie; which feruor ſo ſoone as we have obteined we are exceedingly enabled, with great alacritie to vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertake any worke what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever we thinke to be moſt gratefull vnto almightie God, and for which att laſt we shal be rewarded with aeternal happineſſe. We ſee then that our cheifeſt la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour in prayer muſt be to inflame and ſett our hearts
<pb n="207" facs="tcp:15454:62"/>on fire, with this fervency of charitie, and then, as it were, to ſpinne out our prayer ſo long vntill we ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ve atteined vnto this our end. But when through the wearinſſe of our frayle bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die we find this heate or fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour in vs to grow cold, then muſt we deſiſt and pray no longer, but preſently applie our ſelves to ſome other workes of vertue. For if we shall ſuffer this fervour to be altogether ex tinguished in vs, we doe not onely not ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teine our end intended in prayer, but alſo we giue no ſmal occaſion to induce the contrarie. For ſo ſoone as this fervour by ouroverle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth of prayer shall wax cold or
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:15454:63"/>remiſſe, we are preſently deſtitute and forſaken of all inward comfort, whereby many times it comes to paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe, that our minds are wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering abroad, ſeeking ſome thing pleaſing and delight ful to our ſenſes, which doth often introduce a diſſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion moſt pernitious to our ſoules, and drawes vs by litle and litle into many evills and inconueniences, which had not happened, if we had riſen from prayer before, and not have ſuffered that burning fervour to have been vtterly extinguished in vs and therefore ſaint Auguſtine commendeth cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine Monkes in Egipt, for that they vſed short prayer,
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:15454:63"/>
                     <hi>The brothers in Egipt,</hi> ſayth he,<note place="margin">Epiſt. 121. de ora<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>do Deum</note> 
                     <hi>are ſayd to have often prayers but very short, and as it were ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culatoire.</hi> Therefore doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe they vſed often, that they might often renew this fervor; and short, for no other cauſe, but that the fervour which they had got<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten in prayer, ſhould not grow cold or remiſſe through length of prayer.</p>
                  <p>The cheifeſt care therefore of him that prayeth muſt be to nouriſh, and mainteine this fervour inkinled in his ſoul, and not to ſuffer it to die, nor to deſiſt fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> prayer, ſo long as it may be mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned or increaſed, vnleſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome great wearineſſe of the bodie, and ſoe allwais by
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:15454:64"/>this end we ought to meaſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re the length or ſhortneſſe of our prayer. For as the phiſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tian (hauing reguard to the end of his art, which is the health of this bodie) tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers his medicine and giues it to his patient, not in ſo great a quantitie as he can, but in ſuch as is convenient, eyther for gaigning or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerving the health of his pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient. So he that prayeth muſt not prolong his prayer as long as he can, but ſo long as it is conuenient eyther for the getting or preſerving of this fervour. And when he finds him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe through this vnion with God ſo gently infla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, and ſweetly affected,
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:15454:64"/>let him then goe in ſilence withſighes, and teares full of ioy and loue, and accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plishe the remainder of his deuotions, according as the holy Ghoſt shall inſpire him. For I would councell no man to giue over his prayer, ſo long as this fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour and heate indureth, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe there happens ſome thing which may be more to the honour and glorie of God, or of more neceſſitie to him that prayeth, or mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re profitable to our neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour: But ſoe ſoone as he finds himſelfe through the weakeneſſe, and wearineſſe of his body to be come cold and dull and drie, let him forthwith give ouer, and
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:15454:65"/>content himſelfe ith w<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hat he hath alreadie gai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gned, and applie himſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fe to ſome occaſion or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, fitt for his ſtate and calling, vntill ſome other opportunitie. But if that he be ſtirried vp againe by ſome new affection, let him by no meanes ſuffer it to die; but at leaſt with ſome short and iaculatorie prayer, let him offer it, and himſelfe vp to God, and deſire his clemency towards him. For ſeing this affection, as we may very well imagine pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedes and is ſtirred vpp in him by the holy Ghoſt, he may in no wiſe refuſe it without great ingratitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:15454:65"/>vnto almightie God. Wherefore all buſineſſe layd aſide (ſo farre as neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie will ſuffer) wee muſt follow and cheriſh this mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and not ſuffer it to pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rish, and die in him by his negligence.</p>
                  <p>But heere ſome may ſay vnto me, how can he,<note place="margin">Seculer perſones may at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to prayer</note> poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly who is in this life ſoe troubled with cares, ſo per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexed with worldly occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, and full of buſineſſe, how can he attend ſoe ſtrict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to prayer? Harken a litle to Saint Chriſoſtome, and he will anſwere,<note place="margin">Chry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoſt l. 5. ho. 79. de orat.</note> 
                     <hi>He may and that very eaſily, may though he were in publick court, or if he were preſent before any tribunal, we have not,</hi> ſayth
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:15454:66"/>the <hi>ſuch need of ourſpeech as of our thoughts not of the lifting vp of our hands as of our he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arts If thou haſt thy mind in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flamed thou haſt the perfection of prayer:</hi> thus he. Thou ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yſt pray therefore where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer thou art, though thou beeſt in companie, thou mayeſt for à moment of ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me with draw thy ſelfe,<note place="margin">Prou. 9</note> and by ſtealth offer to God ſome litle prayer as the Scripture ſayth <hi>ſtolne waters are the ſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eter.</hi> And truly prayers thus on the ſuddaine, and by ſtealth, as it were darted vp to heaven, doe oftenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes ſtirre vp our minds more vigorouſly, and more ardently inflame our hearts,<note place="margin">Iacula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torie pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yers.</note> with that moſt excellent
<pb n="215" facs="tcp:15454:66"/>loue of God, and are inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ede (as they affirme whome experience hath taught) moſt acceptable to our he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>auently ſpouſe Chriſt Ieſus: but if thou canſt by no mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes withdraw thy ſelfe from their ſights with whome thou doeſt conuerſe out of the reſpect thou beareſt to them; yet mayeſt thou in their preſence lift vp thy heart to God, whoe, thou art ſure, is preſent with thee, and in a few words ſay vnto him with the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet David, <hi>Intend vnto my ayde,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Pſa. 37. Pſa. 63.</note> 
                     <hi>O Lord God of my ſalvation!</hi> Or this, <hi>incline vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to my ayde o God.</hi> Then which words Caſſianus af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmeth, there can be none
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:15454:67"/>more powerfull and effica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious. If thou ſhalt but in thy heart repeate theſe words, thy prayer ſhal peirce the heavens, and thus much thou maieſt doe whereſoever thou beeſt,<note place="margin">Lib. 1. collat. Patru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> collat. 10.</note> 
                     <hi>Whereſoever thou art,</hi> ſayth S. Chriſoſtome, <hi>thou mayeſt erect thy altare, no place can hinder thee from dedicating thy ſelfe to God,</hi> if thout wer mending they ſhoes or waſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hing dishes or what els ſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, thou mayeſt pray: it is lawfull for the ſervant what buſineſſe ſoever he is about of his maſters, to pray. In the court, in the market place, in the midſt of never ſoe great a multitude of people a man may pray. Saint Paul prayed in the priſon,
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:15454:67"/>the Prophet Hieremie in the durt,<note place="margin">Act. 16 Hier. 38. E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>z ech. 38. Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niel. 9. &amp; 13. Ionae 2 Lu. 23.</note> Ezechias againſt the wall, Daniell in the lions denne, Ionas in the wha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les bellie, the theife on the Croſſe, and all theiſe we<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re heard praying in very few words. All this out of Saint Chriſoſtome in ſeue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall places.</p>
                  <p>Whoſoeuer therefore ſhall exerciſe himlſelfe from ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me to time after this man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, that is, now praying, then doeing ſome other good worke, ſtill imployed eyther to gett this fervour of charitie, or in increa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing or nourishing the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me, never ſuffering it (ſo farre as he is able) tho rough his negligence or fault
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:15454:68"/>to be extinguished, or to grow cold, nor ſuffers the good motions and inſpira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the holy Ghoſt to die in him without ſome fruit, he without all doubt in short time ſhal come vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to that vnſpeakble tranqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie of mind, and to ſuch à pleaſant ioy in heart as incomparablie ſurpaſſeth all wordly ſolace and content<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, all ioy all laughing and meriment, all pleaſure that heere can be affoorded or expected. And thus let vs come to the third quſtion.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="chapter">
                  <pb n="119" facs="tcp:15454:68"/>
                  <head>Wether the prayer of the heart onely is more aduantagious then that which is made both with heart and ſpeech</head>
                  <head>CHAP. IV.</head>
                  <p>IT remaineth now that we treate whether prayer of the heart only, or prayer which is made with the he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>art and lipps together be moſt proffitable vnto him that prayeth I doe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt heere, that it is not my intention, to affirme any thing in derogation of vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call prayer, ſuch as is eyther receiued by cuſtome, or ordeined by the conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the Church, or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:15454:69"/>by way of pennance, or aſſumed by vow or any other promiſe whatſoever, by which a man hath bound himlſelfe to vocall prayer. But my opinion is, that w<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hoſoever is free from theiſe bonds, and in poſſeſſion of his abſolute libertie, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires to ſerve God after the beſt pureſt and moſt pleaſing way vnto him: it is farre mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re proffitable for ſuch an one to pray with his heart only, then with his tongue and heart together: Becauſe as Saint Auguſtine in a certai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne Epiſtle of his to Proba, ſpeaking of the fruit of prayer, affirmeth, ſaying <hi>The office,</hi> of praying, <hi>is better per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed by ſithinge and mourning
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:15454:69"/>then by ſpeech of lipps,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Epiſt. 121.</note> 
                     <hi>better by weeping then ſpeaking.</hi> Which if it be ſo, verily the prayer of the heart, from whence the ſorrow breaketh, is much more availeable then the wordes, which proceede from the lipps. And rightly by cauſe as ſaint Cyprian te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifierh,<note place="margin">De o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne pau lo pòſt princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pium.</note> 
                     <hi>God is the hearer of the heart not of the voyec, he is not to be moved by clamour or noyſe, who ſees the inward thoughts of the mind.</hi> Wherefore a poore Wretch who caſteth himſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fe proſtrate on the earth, with great humilitie ack<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowledging himſelfe to be a ſinner, and laying open his miſeries, pouring forth the bottome of his heart before God, not vttering words,
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:15454:70"/>but pittifull groanes: this poore ſoule without all que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion ſhall ſoone obteine w<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hat he requireth att Gods hand. Which appeares plai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nely to be true in Anna, the mother of Samuell. For ſhe being barren earneſtly deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red att the hands of God, that he would giue her a ſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne, for which cauſe ſhe often frequented the temple, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploring his diuine goodneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe by dayly prayer, that he would be pleaſed to be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitious, vnto her in this her ſuit, yet did ſhe not forme any one word att all, but prayed in hart only, as the Scripture ſayth, <hi>She prayed in her heart and novoyce was heard, for her lipps onely moved.</hi> Why
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:15454:70"/>doe I vſe many words? By this only prayer that is of her heart ſhe obteined what ſhe aſked; for ſhe brought forth a ſonne, whome ſhe with ſo many teares and ſoe much ſorrow had begged att the hands of God, and not with the noyſe of her lipps and tongue. To this alſo doth ſaint Hierome agree expli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cating that of <hi>S.</hi> Mathewe, <hi>But thou when thou prayeſt en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter into thy chamber,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Math. 6.</note> 
                     <hi>and having shutt the dore pray to thy father. It ſeemeth to me,</hi> ſayth he, <hi>we are rather commanded to pray vnto our Lord,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Hier. in cap. 6.</note> 
                     <hi>with our thougts in our breaſt, then with our lipps, as we reade in the booke of Kings, that Anna did, her lipps, ſayth the Scripture were moved, and
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:15454:71"/>hervoyce was not heard.</hi> Thus S. Hier. in this way of prayer vehemently moves his di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine Majeſtie; and powerful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie inclines him ſeedily to heare vs.</p>
                  <p>Moreouer the holy Ghoſt is our teacher and aduiſer to this way of prayer as S. Paul teſtifieth,<note place="margin">Ro. 8.</note> who ſayth, <hi>what we should pray, as we ought we know not; but the ſpiritt himſelfe aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth for vs with groanings in ſpeakeable.</hi> As if he would ſay, we know not after what manner to aske any thing, but the ſpiritt of God inw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ardly ſtirring vp our hearts, makes vs with vnſpeakeable groanings to aske, what is moſt fitting for our ſoules health.</p>
                  <pb n="125" facs="tcp:15454:71"/>
                  <p>Yet notwithſtanding I doe not denie, but that ſome de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uout perſon may beginne his prayer with what wordes he pleaſeth, from his lipps. But ſoe ſoone as ever he ſhall find himſelfe a litle enkindled, and as it were ſet on fire with that ſweet flame of the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ghoſt, then it will be fitt for him to leave of vocall prayer, and follow the lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of the diuine ſpiritt, and in ſile<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce to permit him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe to be wholy gouerned by it. For as I ſayd a litle aboue, the end which we ſhould prefix to our ſelues in our prayer, is cheifely the fervour of charitie, with wh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ich we begin to be poſſeſſed, and inflamed then by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vout
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:15454:72"/>prayer our minds are ſtirred vp and clevated vnto God on high. As ſoone the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>refore as we find our ſelves to have atteined to this end, then muſt we ſtriue by all meanes to continue it in vs: which to doe, without all doubt we have no better way, then to follow the lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of the holy ghoſt, who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe conduct farre more ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vanceth our affaire, then any words we can invent or bring forth. Wherefore muſt wee with all our might fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low the inſtinct and motion of the holy ſpiritt, whether ſoever it ſhall leade vs, ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther neede we from thence forth vtter any words of our owne. Not vnlike vnto him,
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:15454:72"/>who after great labour and long travaile hath paſſed the ſea,<note place="margin">A ſimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litude.</note> and is arrived at his deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red haven, then he forſaketh the ſhipp that brought him, and applieth himſelfe wholy to the end and purpoſe for which he came, and is no more ſollicitous for the poo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re veſſayle that brought him thither: So alſo he that by the helpe and vſe of vocall prayer, as by a ſhipp hath atteined vnto the inward conſolation of his ſoule, and to this fervour of charitie in God, muſt then make it his cheifeſt care and ſtudy, that this fervour by no meanes grow cold, but then leaving of his vocall prayer, he muſt follow this holy ſpirit, who
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:15454:73"/>hath brought him to this fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour, wither ſoever it shall leade him: then he muſt not vſe his owne words: but w<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hatſoever the holy Ghoſt ſhal ſuggeſt vnto his heart, that let him deſire, not with words, but with burning ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hes of ioy.</p>
                  <p>But that thou mayſt more certeinely know that this manner of prayer to wit, which is offered in ſpirit and mind, is more excellent then that which is perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med with ſpeech and words, liſten to that which Chriſt ſayth in the ghoſpell,<note place="margin">Ioa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. 4.</note> 
                     <hi>God is a ſpirit, and they that adore him, muſt adore him in ſpirit and veritie.</hi> Behold as God is a moſt ſpiritual thing, ſo doth
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:15454:73"/>he require a ſacrifice moſt ſpirituall, therefore the prayer offered to him in ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit and mind is more acce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptable then that, which is of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered with the groſſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nountiation of words, which cannot be formed vithout corporall ayre. And let it not trouble thee that it is ſaid in ſaint Iohn, <hi>adorare</hi> to, <hi>adore</hi> and not, <hi>orare</hi> to <hi>pray,</hi> for the one of theiſe cannot be donne without the other, for when God is prayed vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, then is he truly adored, and when he is adored, then is he alſo prayed vnto. God then requires, you ſee, to be adored in ſpirit and mind, of the moſt ſpirituall and elevated minds, for ſuch as
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:15454:74"/>theſe he ſeeketh after, as S. Iohn ſayth to adore him. Wherefore I feare not to ſay, that ſpirituall men, who have carefully exerciſed themſelves in this manner of prayer, and have had theire hearts alwayſe lifted vp to God, and have taſted of the ſweetneſſe of this fervour, (I fcare not I ſay to affirme) that they have much more profited by this prayer of the heart, then if they had repeated innumerable pſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes and prayers, as very many doe, overburthening their minds, and by that meanes ſo excluding them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves from the end of their prayer, that they never taſt any ſpirituall ſweetneſſe att all.</p>
                  <pb n="131" facs="tcp:15454:74"/>
                  <p>And without all queſtion, the deſire of running over ſuch a multitude of prayers, doth oftentimes hinder and divert Gods holy viſitation from their hearts, which otherwiſe he would be very readie to give them. Forli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keas the ſunne ſends forth the beames of light to euery place, ſo is almightie God moſt readie to powre into euery one of vs this boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous ſweetneſſe, if the paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſages into our minds be not with our multitude of words, as with certeine thike and condenſed clouds, hindered and blockt vp; whereas we should be intent to nothing att all but God, and that with all our deſires, and minds, if
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:15454:75"/>we wilbe pertakers of this ſweetneſſe. But ſuch perſons attend not to God, but to the quicke pronouncing of a great many words, neyther doe they conſider the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of his diuine Majeſtie, but with how great celeritie, and ſpeede they can runne over ſuch a number of pſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes, and prayers, with which ſtudie and deſire, they doe ſo buſie and ouerwhelme theire minds, as not one dropp, of this ſweetneſſe can fall vpon them: and yet they perſwade themſelves that they pleaſe God moſt, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomuch that they cannot ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfie rheir conſciences, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till they have prayed their ſtinted number of deuotio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s.
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:15454:75"/>And if by chance any part of them (I doe not meane of ſuch as are commanded by the Church, but which they have vndertaken of their ow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne accord to ſay) be left vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſayd; alas poore ſoules, how great a ſcruple doe they for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me in their conſciences? How miſerablie doe they torture their minds? Not marking that ſaint Hierome ſayth,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Citet by Gratian in cap.</hi> no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diocri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter de conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne diſt. 5.</note> 
                     <hi>The ſaying or repeating of fiue pſalmes with puritie of heart, and ſpirituall ioy, is better then the repeating of the whole pſalter, with a troubled and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtracted mind.</hi> And it is much more to be wondred at, that they will not marke what Chriſt ſayth in the ghoſpell admoniſhing them that pray,
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:15454:76"/>
                     <hi>When ye are praying, ſpeake not much:</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Mat. 6</note> yet muſt you not thinke, that Chriſt is diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſed with long prayer ſeing it is read of himſelfe that <hi>He was long in prayer,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Luc. 6.</note> but that we ſhould not truſt in the multitude of our prayers, and eſpeciallie the affection of the mind being not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, nor that we should thinke him to be more mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved with the multitude of words, then the affection of the heart. But contrary, he is more moved with one only true affectionate and inward lifting vp of the mind, then with all the prayers we can ſay, voyd of affection. Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reupon ſaint Auguſtin ſayth,<note place="margin">Epiſt. 121. ad</note> 
                     <hi>It is one thing to ſpeake much, it
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:15454:76"/>is an other to be well affected.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Proba cap. 10</note> He ſpeaketh much to God that ſure thinketh he can move his clemency by a long and a numerous company of words, by which God is not moved att all; but with the ſincere affections of the ſou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le. For the clamour or noyſe of the tougne maketh a very dull ſound in his eares, and the vehement burning of the affection moveth him in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly, becauſe God is mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re delighted with our affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions then voyces, and them moſt that are accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panied with ſighes and tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res. For this manner of praying doth as it were over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come God, who otherwiſe is inuincible, and this doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:15454:77"/>is better performed and offered to God in ſpirit and mind, then with any words formed with the mouth. For the ſpirit ſoe ſoone as it is moved and a litle ſett on fire, executeth its office with farre more ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leritie, then the motion of the lipps, or the corporal for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming of words is able to doe. By which that is made appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent, which we have ſo long diſcourſed of, to witt that the prayer of the mind and ſpirit onely is more power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful with God, and more to be eſteemed and practized by vs. For the motion and agitation of the lipps is ſlo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer, and the corporal weight of the tongue pronouncing
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:15454:77"/>the words is leſſe apt for the purpoſe. And not onely this, but the now opening now shutting of the mouth is mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re laborious, then that it can aſſiſt the ſpirit or mind in any thing, eſpeciallie it being once inflamed and ſet on fire by this diuine love. For then it is caried with ſo great celeritie and ſwiftneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe, that neyther the lipps, mouth, or tongue are able to follow it, and if they doe follow, they helpe it in no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, but are rather trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſome and full of moleſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
                  <p>I could wish therefore that who are delighted in prayer, and willingly ſpend their ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me in it, and cheifely ſuch
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:15454:78"/>as haue both time and leyſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re enough to imploy the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rein, I could wish, I ſay, they would not ſoe vnproffitably burthen themſelues, with ſo great a multitude of vocal prayers; but that time (vhich they ſpend in them) to ſo litle profitt, they would ſpe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d in ſetting their affections on fire towards God, that ſo at laſt they may atteine to ſome taſt of that vnſpeakable ſweetneſſe, which God que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtionleſſe will powre vpon their ſoules. which will eaſilie be brought to paſſe, if that they doe worthily prepare themſelues, and proceede to the manner we haue before ſet downe. That is, firſt, that they offer themſelues in all
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:15454:78"/>humilitie to God, then di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligently performe their prayers with a true and iuſt attention of mind; and la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtly doe their beſt indeavour to finish their prayers with all attention of heart. They may alſo beginne their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uotions with ſome vocall prayer, ſuch as they haue heeretofore been accuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to be inflamed with; but then finding themſelves thus inflamed, ſweetly affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted, and drawne by al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mightie God, in Gods name leaving off their vocall prayer, let them with teares and ſighes follow the tract of the holy ghoſt, whither ſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer it shal leade them, then begging inſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly at the hands
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:15454:79"/>of almightie God whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the holy ſpirit ſhal inſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re them, but cheifely that it would pleaſe, his diuine Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſtie not to forſake them, but that he would graciouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie grant them what in his diuine knowledge and wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, he ſeeth moſt neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarie for theire ſoules health. And if they proceede accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to this manner, they shal not only grow and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come more acceptable to God, but ſhall alſo dayly profitt more and more in fervour of charitie, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come like vnto thoſe moſt heavenly and angelicall ſpiritts, which dayly behold and contemplate the face of God. And why ſhould they
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:15454:79"/>not (though heere lying vpon earth and couered with this corruptible flesh) be ſayd to be like Angells? Seing they pray as the ble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Angells doe, that is in ſpirit, ſeing alſo they taſt the ſame ſweetneſſe which the bleſſed Angells doe, and ſeing laſtly they doe heere on earth find in themſelues a pledge or earneſt peny of their future happineſſe, which theſe bleſſed Angells doe now inioy? In ſoe much that there is nothing wa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ting to them but the beatificall viſion of Gods glory, which ſo ſoone as they haue shaken of this vayle of mortall flesh they ſhall inioy in heaven.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="notice">
            <pb facs="tcp:15454:80"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Gentle Reader, by reaſon of theſe vacant pages, I thought good in reſpect this litle Armour of S. Ephraem, doth ſomething conduce to the preſent Diſcourſe to adde it as a poſtſcript for thy fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther inſtruction.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="142" facs="tcp:15454:80"/>
            <head>THE ARMOVR OF S. EPHRAEM.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>E who reſolveth to fight couragi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly for Chriſt Ieſus, muſt poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſe himſelfe of this ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour, with which being guarded, he may both reſiſt his aduerſarie the devill, and be more pleaſing in the ſight of God our Saviour. What this Panoplie or armour is liſten (my brother) and I will tell thee. For thy breaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plate or doublett take fayth,
<pb n="242" facs="tcp:15454:81"/>but as a graine of muſtard ſeede, beleeving in the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſubſtantiall and individuall Trinitie:<note place="margin">Hovv fayt bis compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to a graine of runſtard ſeede.</note> For the graine of muſtard ſeede is very light and round, having neyther cracke nor corner: but (as I ſayd before) is altogether round, which being pounded or bruiſed hath in it a mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailous great heate. The Prince of the Apoſtolicall order S. Peter, when he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed Chriſt Ieſus to be ſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne of the living God, he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived the keyes of the Kingdome of heaven,<note place="margin">Matt. 16.</note> and obteined power ouer all hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly and earthly things this harneſſe or armour (deare brother) challenge to thy ſelfe, that thou for
<pb n="243" facs="tcp:15454:81"/>mayſt receiue grace from God for whoſoever hath but ſo much perfect fayth and charitie shall without que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion promerit grace from God. Which our Lord inſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuating ſayd.</p>
            <p>If you have fayth as a graine of muſtard ſeede, ſay to this montaine, remoue fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hence thither and it shall remoue.<note place="margin">The pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit and come<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of fayth.</note> Doe you not ſee that fayth promeritts grace? Vnto it is giuen the ſpirit of vnderſtanding, truly a moſt ſingular gift for when one belecveth, then alſo he vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtandeth: It is giuen him to vnderſtand, that he ſhould not iudge his neighbour: then is given to him the ſpeach of wiſedome, then
<pb n="244" facs="tcp:15454:82"/>the grace of curing, for he doth cure the weake in fayth, and bringeth to right, thoſe that are falen: for one and the ſame ſpirit worketh all theſe things. But there be many who have fayth, but are deſtitute of workes: But that is no fayth, for it is dead: for fayth without wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes is dead.<note place="margin">Iac. 2.25.</note> He that hath fayth and worketh theworkes of fayth: he hath fayth bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning as the muſtard ſeede. Poſſeſſe thou this my bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and be ſound and firme in fayth: and fervent to put in execution the preceps of our Saviour, that thou mayeſt deſerue to heare that voyce of his. Welfare thee good and faythful fervant, enter into
<pb n="245" facs="tcp:15454:82"/>the ioy of thy Lord.<note place="margin">Matt. 25.</note> Our Lord calls him good for his works, faythfull for his fayth. Take the helmet hope of the future good, which neyther eye hath ſeene, care hath heard, nor hath entred into the heart of man, vpon which the Angells deſire to looke. For this hope is the moſt powerfull conſolation of the ſoule,<note place="margin">Hope the helmet.</note> amongſt the thornes of her afflictions and mole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtations, and the memorie thereof will repleniſh thee with ioy. To this being in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent the holy Martyrs of Chriſt amidſt their various and moſt horrible torments, a midſt bales of iron, ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red all, moſt readilie and willingly, being ſtrengh the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned
<pb n="246" facs="tcp:15454:83"/>with this moſt eminent vertue of hope. Moyſes pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fixing before his eyes the reward of this hope, refuſed to be called the ſonne of the Queene, eſteming and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferring it before all threaſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res of Egypt wherefore he made rather choyce to be afflicted with the people of God then to haue any tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall fruition of ſinne Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce this hope my brother day<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly before thine eyes, that affection to it may not per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit thee to eſteeme any whit of temporal and corruptible things, and not onely this, but that it may make thee more prompt, and ready to aduance thy ſelfe to any good worke. For thy girdle
<pb n="247" facs="tcp:15454:83"/>girt thy ſelfe with perfect charitie to God and thy neyghbour,<note place="margin">Charitie the gir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle.</note> and this will ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke thee runne forward wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hout any impediment at all. For if he whoe is girt with his girdle, doth ſoe eaſily paſſe with the burthen he vndertaketh, with how much more facilitie shal he who is girt with this diuine chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie overcome all things? For charitie ſuffers all things, beareth with all things, cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie is the fulneſſe of the law. Saint Paul being poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſed of this charitie, ſayd, who is weake and I am not weake? Who is ſcandalized and I am not burned? Haſt thou ſeene the pittie and compaſſion of charitie? O
<pb n="248" facs="tcp:15454:84"/>bleſſed ſaint Paul, why art thou ſo afflicted for me? Shalt thou ſuffer torments for me? Thou haſt once con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſummated thy courſe, thou haſt kept thy fayth, and the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re is a crowne of iuſtice layd vp for thee, what wouldeſt thou haue more? Why doeſt thou afflict thy ſelfe? And why should eſt thou become weake for me? Alas ſayth he it is charitle that vrgeth me. Haſt thou now ſeene the heigth and eminencye of charitie? He who through charitie had fulfilled the law, being yet couered with his mortall and corruptible flesh, deſerved to be rapt vp to the third heaven, and to heare ſuch words, as are not
<pb n="249" facs="tcp:15454:84"/>lawful for man to ſpeake. Now forthy shoes take vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thee humilitie;<note place="margin">Numili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie the shoe.</note> for as the ſhoe is continually ſpurned and trodd vpon: even ſo he that is replenished with humilitie, ſtudyeth to be tro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den on by all men. Therefo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re thou (o my brother) fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nish thy ſelfe with this ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue of humilitie, for it is tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly a ſhoe, not corporal, but ſpirituall, and it shall preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue thee that thou shalt not ſtrike they foot againſt the ſtone. For Chriſt is the ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne, and humilitie shal ſo preſerue thee, that thou of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fendeſt not Chriſt. The Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet Dauid abounded in hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militie,<note place="margin">Pſal. 90.</note> when he ſayd: I am a worme, and not a man.
<pb n="250" facs="tcp:15454:85"/>Doeſt thou ſee this royall humilitie of this King and Prophet?<note place="margin">Pſal. 21.</note> He alwayſe ſawe our Lord before him, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he was in his ſight keeping him, that he ſhould not be moved that is, not fall in to ſinne.<note place="margin">Humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie moſt gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re full to God.</note> By this thou ſeeſt (moſt deare brother) how highly allmighty God lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth humilitie, who is alw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ayſe neere at hand to him, that is indued with it, and all wayſe looketh vpon him. For it is written.<note place="margin">Pſal. 112. Pſalm. 10.</note> He who dwelleth on high, reſpecteth the humble, and againe his eyes lookes vpon the poore. But my deare brother when thou heareſt this word poo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re; doe not apprehend one that wants worldly fortune,
<pb n="251" facs="tcp:15454:85"/>For many Kings haue highly pleaſed God,<note place="margin">Vvhois truly poore. <hi>Mat. 5.</hi>
               </note> and many beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gars have perished. But poo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re here, is poore in ſpirit: ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to theiſe words: Bleſſed are the poore in ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit becauſe theirs is the Kingdome of heaven:<note place="margin">1. Pet. 2.</note> Soe dearely beloued, humble thy ſelfe vnder the mightie hand of God,<note place="margin">Matt. 18.</note> that he may exalt thee in the Kingdome of heaven, which our Saviour hath promiſedvnto the hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble. For thy Targett or Buc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kler, arme thy ſelfe with the ſigne of the Croſſe,<note place="margin">The Croſſe che bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ckier.</note> ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning therewith all thy body and thy heart, and not onely with thy hand, but euen with thy very mind, all thy ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies and end eauours, thy en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trance
<pb n="252" facs="tcp:15454:86"/>into any place, and thy going forth, thy ſitting downe alſo and thy riſing vp, thy bed, and whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver thou doeſt, ſigne it firſt in the name of the father and of the ſonne and of the holy Ghoſt: for this is a moſt ſtrong armour or defence, and none can ever hurt thee, if thou beeſt ſigned with it. For if one that carieth the protection of an earthly King, noe man dareth af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>front him, how much more ought we not to feare, bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the protection of our heavenly Emperour? Vſe therefore (deare brother) theiſe armes in all thy ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions they are preualent againſt the enimie; yea
<pb n="253" facs="tcp:15454:86"/>againſt the ſword, which is bitter and malevolent an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger. For this two - edged ſword killeh in a moment it ſtriketh,<note place="margin">Anger the ſvv ord of the eni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie.</note> as it is written a moment of wrath, is his ruine.<note place="margin">Eccl. 1.</note> Therefore my dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re brother never neglect to ſigne thy ſelfe, and thou shalt breake the netts the devill layeth to enſnare thee, as it is written, in the way that I walked in they haue layed a net for me.<note place="margin">Pſal. 139.</note> Be therefore dayly ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gned with the Croſſe, and noe evill will come nee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re thee.</p>
            <p>For thy bowe lift vp thy hands in prayer as it is writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten.<note place="margin">Prayer the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vve.</note> And thou haſt made my armes as a bowe of ſteele.
<pb n="254" facs="tcp:15454:87"/>For verily the hands of him who prayeth in Knowledge are as a bowe of ſteele againſt his enemies, or as an arrow directly and forciblie shott by the bowbender. For if in prayer you ſuffer your mind to wander: you wilbe iuſt as he that holdeth à bow in his hand, but cannot di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect his arrow againſt his adverſarie, shooting it att Randome and without ad vice. Yet ſometimes it ſtriketh ſome feare in thy enimie, when he ſeeth thee bend thy bow, though the arrowe come not ſo neere him, but a diſtance of: Soe I ſay my bretheren, when one prayeth with devotion, and ſuffers not his thoughts
<pb n="255" facs="tcp:15454:87"/>to be wandring abroad, but vnderſtands to whome he prayeth, that this ſuch pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yer tendeth to God himſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fe, then is the enimie moſt vehemently contriſtated, as being peirced through the heart with a sharpe dart. For how much more the ſoule profiteth in grace, ſo much further of doth he flie,<note place="margin">Pſal. 34.</note> as the duſt before the face of the wind, for the Angell of God doth perſecute him; fee in what thing he wounds him thus,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 14.</note> becauſe he pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yeth in devotion and know ledge, and he is more ſtreng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thened, becauſe he reſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yneth his thoughts and ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers them not to wander ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roade. And thou O my bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="256" facs="tcp:15454:88"/>powre forth thy pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yers in knowledge But if whilſt thou prayeſt thy mind be diſtracted, eyther by the wandering of thy eye, or the catching of thy eare, or evagation of thy thoughts, or by any other cauſe, know this to be his working: yet make not to much haſt to end thy prayer, but rebuke thy ſelfe, and recollect thy ſpiritts, and then againe pray in know ledge that thou mayeſt know for whome thou prayeſt vnto God, and for what thou prayeſt; and vſe not many and ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluous words. For it is the worke of the devill to ſcat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter our thoughts vpon ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny impertinent things, and
<pb n="257" facs="tcp:15454:88"/>he doth not willingly ſuffer vs to perſiſt in the intention we firſt made. For he know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth full well, that if a man perſeuereth, he that made him will heare him, not with ſtanding he hath com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted innumerable ſinnes. wherefore he ſuggeſteth many idle and ſuperfluous words and thoughts, that the mind being repulſed from her firſt intention, may wander through various dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tractions and our firſt inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of prayer be diuerted to ſome other thing. where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore my brother,<note place="margin">Vve muſtaſke of God vvhat is moſt ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarie for vs.</note> demand of god, what vrgeth thee moſt and for thoſe things thou haſt moſt neede of Remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber thoſe two blind men
<pb n="258" facs="tcp:15454:89"/>crying after him: Haue mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy vpon vs (ſonne of David) what ſayd our lord vnto them?<note place="margin">Mat. 9.20. Marc 10. Lu. 18.</note> but, what will you that I doe vnto you? And they according to the greife and affection of their heart, requeſted that their eyes might be opened. Did they aske any other thing, of whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ch they ſtoode in very gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>at neede? Did they ſay, giue vs a garment to couer vs, for we are very poore? Noe cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, but they asked God, that, of which they ſtood moſt in need.<note place="margin">Mat. 15 Mar. 7.</note> Behold the woman of Canaan crying and ſaying vnto him: lord haue mercy vpon me for my daughter is ſore vexed with a deuill, and ſayd nothing
<pb n="259" facs="tcp:15454:89"/>els, but vttered the greife and affection of her heart: in fine all that euer came to our Lord and Saviour, what did they but lay open before him the afflictio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s and greife of their hearts? Did not alſoe that woman, which was troubled with the bloodie flux, come vnto him, and deſired him to ſtopp it? who I pray you goeing to the phiſitian or chirurgian,<note place="margin">Mat. 9. Mar. 5. Luc. 8. Eſa. 6.</note> doth not forth with open the very bottome of his diſeaſe or wound? Doe thou alſo my deare brother, offer vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him the greife of thy ſoule, behold him with thy ſpiritual and intellectuall eyes of fayth, ſitting vpon a moſt high and eleuated thro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne,
<pb n="260" facs="tcp:15454:90"/>and troopes of Angells and Archa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gells aſſiſting rou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d about him, and caſting thy ſelfe before the ſight of his goodneſſe, powre forth thy prayers before him, firſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſing thy ſinns, then in hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militie and deuotion, vrging thy neceſſities vnto him, and the ſorrowes of thy heart, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till he ſhall in his goodneſſe and clemencie haue mercy vpon the, ſaying, ô faithfull ſoule, be it vnto thee as thou deſireſt. But withalle ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke this councell, my bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, if he ſhall delay, and not forthwith grant thy peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, yet deſiſt not to crye vnto him. Remember the Cananaean, and imitate her perſeuerance, for ſhe ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red
<pb n="261" facs="tcp:15454:90"/>ſhort delay, and had not her petition ſo qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ckely granted, in ſo much that the Diſciples came vnto our Lord and intre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in her behalfe, and ſayd, Diſmiſſe her for ſhe cryeth after vs. Let vs by example learne to perſiſt in prayer, if we doe not ſpee dily obteine what we aſke. And our Saviour ſayth which of you having a freind, and he ſhall come to him by night and ſay, Freind lend me three loaves, becauſe my freind is come vnto me, and I have none to put before him, and he anſwereth from with in, and ſayth, good freind, doe not trouble me, my dores are ſhutt, and my
<pb n="262" facs="tcp:15454:91"/>children are in bed with me, I cannot riſe to giue them thee: and he ſtill knocketh on, I ſay vnto you, that al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though he doth not riſe and giue him as his freind, yet for to avoyd his importuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, he will giue him ſo many as he hath neede of. And I ſay vnto you, aſke and it ſhall be giuen vnto you, as like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe it is ſayd in the pſalme, <hi>Expecting I haue expected our Lord,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 39.</note> 
               <hi>and he hath attended vnto me, and hath heard my prayers.</hi> Wherefore my brother, grow not in thy prayer ſlac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke and dull, but expect, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt, knocke hard, and thou ſhalt haue, ſoe much as thou haſt neede of. Liſten vnto me deare brother, and
<pb n="263" facs="tcp:15454:91"/>imbrace my councell. If thou aſkeſt any thing at Gods ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds, doe not requeſt it preſently, and prefix him not a time when thou wouldeſt haue it, but leaue it wholy to him and to his divine will. As for exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple, thou art many times vexed and perplexed with euill vncleane thoughts, att which thou art much affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted, and thou prayeſt God that he would free thee from this conflict, yet, my bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, it is many times expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient for thee to be thus tryed. Looke vpon that moſt excellent pillar of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, how for his profit and aduantage the ſting of the flesh the very Angell of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 12.</note> was giuen him, which
<pb n="264" facs="tcp:15454:92"/>beate him and boxed him leaſt he should grow proud.<note place="margin">1. Cor. 12.</note> If then he which was of ſoe excellent and great meritts, was thus exerciſed, leaſt he should grow proud; how much more neede haue we poore weake ones whoe ſtill thinke our ſelues ſome thing to be thus beaten and cuffed, that we growe not inſolent and proud in heart.<note place="margin">Gal. 6.</note> And if againe any other tribulation fall vpon thee, doe not in thy prayer limitt a time whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he shall preciſely free thee from it; for it is many times expedient that thou ſuffer this alſo. For it happens ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny times when thou prayeſt, that thou doeſt not ſoe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> know what is good for thy
<pb n="265" facs="tcp:15454:92"/>ſoules health; as Iſraëll ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered. For <hi>Iſrael did eate and was filled,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Deut. 32.</note> 
               <hi>and my beloued kic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked backe, he grewe fatt, he waxed ouer luſtie, he grew proud and forſooke God his maker.</hi> If thou againe prayeſt to obta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ine any thing doe not deſire it to be immediately granted thee, For it falls out many times that thou being a man, thinkeſt this thing expedie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t for thee, when indeede it is not: But if forſaking thyne owne will, thou reſigne thy ſelfe to the will of God, and according to that, goe on, thou art ſecure. For he who knew all things before they were and are, gouerneth and diſpoſeth all according to his owne benignitie and
<pb n="266" facs="tcp:15454:93"/>pleaſure. For we know not whether that we aske at Gods hands be expedient for vs or noe, ſeinge that ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they haue obteyned what they haue asked of God, afterwards haue been very ſorry, and haue oftentimes fallen into great defects and euills, becauſe they did not diligently ſearch, whether that which they deſired was agreeable to the will of God; but thinking it ſoe, haue been deluded by the devill, and vnder the ſhape and pretext of vertue and iuſtice haue been ſeduced and caſt into many dangers, and ſuch petitions are many times wayted one by greife and repentance whilſt euery
<pb n="267" facs="tcp:15454:93"/>one followes thedeſire and concupiſcence of his owne heart. Harken vnto the Apoſtle, ſaying, <hi>For we know not what we should pray for as we ought:</hi> and againe <hi>All things are lawfull for me,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 8. 1. Cor. 9.10. Ibid.</note> 
               <hi>but all things are not expedient for me. All things are lawfull for me, but all things doe not edifie; he onely knoweth, what is expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient for vs, and what doth edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie vs.</hi> And this I doe wish should beleft and referred to his will, not that I pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibite thee to aske what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer thou deſireſt from him, for I rather pray thee and admonish thee, that thou shouldeſt aske all things from him from the leaſt to the greateſt; but
<pb n="268" facs="tcp:15454:94"/>that when thou doeſt pray and lay thy heart open be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him, thou shouldeſt ſay. <hi>But let not my owne will, but thine be donne; if what I aske be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pedient doe as thou knoweſt:</hi> for ſoe the ſcripture adviſeth vs ſaying. <hi>Reveale vnto our Lord thyway, and hope in him, and he will doe it.</hi> Behold our Lord Ieſus-Chriſt praying in our flesh, which he aſſumed, and ſaying: <hi>Father if it be poſsible, lett this chalice part from me, but not as I will, but as thou wilt.</hi> Wherefore <hi>(deere brother)</hi> if thou doeſt aske any thing of God,<note place="margin">A short prayer for the obtey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of things neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie.</note> perſiſt, in thy petition, ſaying: Lord if it be thy will I shall ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teine what I demand of thee; doe thou permitt it to proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per,
<pb n="269" facs="tcp:15454:94"/>and be effected, but if it be not thy will and plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure permitt it not O my God, to come to paſſe. I humblie beſeech thee not to deliuer me to my owne con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupiſcence, for thou know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt my follie, but preſerue me vnder the shadowe of thy protection, as thou beſt knoweſt, and gouerne me, and direct me, O my God, for thy owne mercyes ſake. But if thou doeſt pray aga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inſt any tribulation or vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleane thoughts ſay with the Prophett. Lord rebuke me not in thy furie, nor chaſtiſe me in thy wrath: Lord haue mercy vpon me for I am weake, but looke, vpon me O Lord, and ſee that I am
<pb n="270" facs="tcp:15454:95"/>earth and duſt and ashes, and can beare nothing. De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuer me not O Lord to my ſinns, for then I shalbe like vnto thoſe that deſcend into the lake: But forgetting my wickedneſſe giue glory to thy owne name, And doe not remember I beſeech thee my ſinns, but thy owne mercyes towards me, and hearken vnto my prayer: And if it be poſſible lett this tribulation paſſe from mee; but not as I will O Lord, but as thou pleaſeſt, Only ſtrengthen my ſoule and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend me, that I may beare it patiently, and find grace before thee in this world and in the next. And caſt thy thoughts vpon him and
<pb n="271" facs="tcp:15454:95"/>he will doe what is fitt for thee. For know this that he being good and full of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nignitie, willeth all things, that are for our ſoules health, for he, the good shepheard layed downe his ſoule, for all vs his sheepe. To him beglory world without end. Amen.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
